Codey: Hello, farmers, and welcome to another episode of the harvest season.
Codey: My name is Cody.
Kelly: And my name is Kelly.
Codey: And we are here to talk today to talk about cottage core games.
Codey: Oh, woo-hoo, specifically bugs, and specifically silk songs.
Kelly: Woo!
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: When, uh, we decided to do Bug Month, I told Al, like, you do realise that means we can't, like, you can't hold off silk song anymore.
Codey: Not that he was, but like, it's happening.
Codey: It's got to happen.
Codey: Um, and of course, I can't do silk songs with anyone other than Kelly.
Codey: Because
Kelly: I think it was, it was meant to be, like, you know, we pushed it off without realising that it had a moment that we were waiting for.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: But I feel like we're just, we're both so, like, I love our friendship because we're both so just like,
Codey: Eh, you'll pop back into my life.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, we'll figure this out.
Codey: Like, we'll talk again eventually.
Kelly: It'll come back around.
Codey: It'll come back around, like neither of us are like, where did she go?
Kelly: Don't worry.
Kelly: Yeah, and I know you were like so busy with like uh, everything.
Codey: It was just fine.
Kelly: I think you were like starting your dissertation or like.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: I think I was fin- I was writing it.
Kelly: Finishing it up.
Codey: I was writing that, um, plus I was finishing like some of my, I, there was just, it's been a while.
Kelly: Yeah, that's what it was.
Codey: been a lot that's been going on in the last almost years.
Codey: It's almost been a year that this game has been out.
Codey: My goodness.
Codey: Um, so yeah.
Codey: Uh, but that's what we're going to talk today about, uh, at the end of my bug rant because of course this is a bug month episode.
Codey: So there will be, what is, uh, what is in the show notes as Cody's entomology corner.
Codey: Um, but it's really, this is the bulk of the episode, and then we sprinkle a little bit of a talk.
Codey: Because I do like to yap.
Codey: And we don't have any news.
Codey: Um, this episode, uh, after Bug Month is done.
Codey: There will be a big news episode, I'm sure.
Codey: But before we jump into like my entomology corner, Kelly, what have you been up to?
Codey: If you've been listening to anything, reading anything, watching anything fun?
Kelly: Um, I did watch a crazy stop motion last weekend, uh, called Mad God.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um, so it was made by Phil Tippet, who worked on all of like the old Star Wars, um, Uh, Oh my god, I'm blanking on the word, but like all of the pieces to the old Star Wars that they used to actually shoot the movie when everything was physical.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: So he spent 30 years building all of the pieces for this movie.
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Kelly: And it's a very odd and graphic and uh, disturbing and confusing movie.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um, but like also so incredible to see like a whole world built like that in stop motion.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, so...
Kelly: Like, I want to tell people to watch it, but also, like, it's a lot as well.
Codey: So, if you, so, I mean, like the, I guess the question would be who, it's like the, if you liked blank, you should see blank.
Kelly: Oh, man.
Codey: Like, do you have a thing?
Kelly: Well.
Kelly: So it is a horror movie, but like it's kind of existential.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um...
Codey: Like psychological horror.
Kelly: Kind of like.
Codey: And also physical.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, um, hmm.
Kelly: I genuinely don't know.
Codey: Okay, well, did you enjoy it?
Kelly: I did, I did enjoy it.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: I think, um, uh, I was left questioning a lot of it at first, but like after thinking about it, I was like, I do want to watch this again because, like, it was very interesting.
Codey: What's the most?
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um,
Kelly: But besides that, I've been playing esoteric ebb, which is like a D&D, um, RPG.
Kelly: Uh, I don't know if you've played like Disco Elysium, but it's very similar to that.
Codey: Uh, I have not, but I know the I know about of it, so.
Kelly: So if you do like games like Disco Elysium, it's very similar to that, I would recommend people who like that game to play that.
Kelly: And it's like mediaeval.
Codey: Well, that's I, I'm a sucker for like the fantasy, like mediaeval realm of things.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, I am also not in a place to do like a story, though.
Kelly: No, and it's so unlike Disco Elysium, which has like a ton of voice acting, this is all reading.
Codey: Mm.
Kelly: So I think the game would not have taken me as long if I was not trying to read every single ounce of information.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: That can be really difficult because, like, you might be really into it like one time that you're playing, but then you might pick up the game and be like, I just want to hack and slash.
Codey: But, but, but you can't because you have to read.
Kelly: Mm-hmm, exactly.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: So I guess technically I was playing and reading that.
Kelly: Um, what have you been up to?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, so I, I've seen the Odyssey.
Codey: Um, I liked that a lot.
Kelly: Oh, nice.
Codey: Um, I also overcame, uh, something in that.
Codey: So someone in the theatre was, there were a couple, a young couple, um, maybe 4 or 5 seats to my left that were talking almost the entire movie.
Kelly: Hmm.
Codey: And I think, like, I had noticed it and it was bothering me for probably like a half an hour. And then I looked at my phone and I realised we were only like an hour and 20 minutes into a 3 hour plus movie. And so I told my friend that I was with.
Codey: I was like, mm, I'm going to go say something.
Codey: So I, uh, conquered my fear of conflict.
Codey: Um, in that moment.
Kelly: Good for you.
Kelly: That's hard to do, you know, it really is.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: and they were totally fine.
Kelly: But also you're allowed to enjoy your movie experience, you know?
Codey: Yeah, and like, I didn't do any, like, and no one else was like shushing them or anything, but it's just like, I am unable to focus on what's happening in front of me because you guys, they're talking loud enough that I could almost hear their conversation and almost understand what they were talking about.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And it was definitely not about the movie, which is wild that you like paid however much money to come into like a well, like a movie that has been well regarded or whatever, and you're just going to yap the whole time.
Codey: So maybe...
Kelly: That upsets me so much.
Codey: Though maybe, like now that I'm thinking about it, they might have been, so I thought they were like an undergrad, they were undergrads or something, but I wonder if they were teenagers and they just wanted to spend time together, but their parents wouldn't let them.
Codey: And so they were just like, what's the longest movie that we can, but they weren't like making out or anything.
Kelly: Mm.
Codey: They were literally just talking and they were like cuddling, but it was, they were just talking. And, yeah.
Codey: So I went over and I was like, hey, like, could you please stop talking?
Codey: And they were like, 0 my gosh, we're so sorry.
Codey: I'm like, it's okay.
Codey: Thank you.
Kelly: Oh, that's good that they had like a good reaction because, yeah, so they probably just did not realise whatsoever, like, which is...
Codey: Oh, they were very like.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Sometimes people are just not aware, but like, um,
Kelly: No, I've had that issue come up at concerts, uh, where like the person behind me will just like literally be talking and like I try to give them,
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: You know, grace to see if they'll stop.
Kelly: And like, what was it?
Kelly: I was at like a modest mouse concert.
Kelly: And this woman was speaking through 7 songs.
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Kelly: And like, I have a high pitched voice and she had a very high pitched voice also, and I know that that carries.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like, I know my voice carries in between like the basiness of like all of the music coming off the stage, you know?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: She was talking about like absolutely nothing related to the concert, like at top volume.
Kelly: So I finally turned around and I was like, I'm so sorry, like, you know, can you please like lower your voice?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like, that's all I can hear. And she like flipped out on me.
Codey: Oh my god.
Kelly: And I was like, okay, well, I paid to be here to listen to the music, not you, so you can move or shut up.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like, I don't care.
Kelly: I am standing here.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: And she had an attitude with me.
Kelly: Like to try to be tough and then she shut up.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: So I was like, well, you thought you were tough, but like, I don't care.
Codey: Yeah, I don't care.
Kelly: Yeah, I just want to enjoy the concert.
Codey: Just let me listen.
Codey: And like...
Codey: Yeah, and like 7 songs, some bands only have like a limited set list.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: It's like you,
Codey: That's basically like, that might be almost all of the songs at that point.
Kelly: Yeah, I I like knew that they had like the, I think it was like halfway through.
Kelly: So I was like, because they were doing an album.
Codey: Okay.
Codey: Got it.
Kelly: But I was like, okay, this is Absolutely absurd.
Kelly: Like, this is too long now.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like I, I let you talk for 7 songs.
Kelly: Please shut up.
Codey: Please.
Kelly: Go stand by the bar if you want to talk, like.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, just somewhere else.
Kelly: But it's, it's hard, so good job, you know, getting up and going to talk to them because I definitely spend like that time also, amping myself up to.
Codey: Thank you.
Codey: Yeah, there was like, like I told my friend about it and he's like, oh, I can't really hear him.
Codey: And then at one point he leaned over.
Codey: He was like, okay, I can kind of hear him now.
Codey: like I get it.
Codey: But he was like on the other side of me.
Codey: And then, like, I was like, I'm going to go say something and he's like, I'm proud of you, go for it.
Codey: I just knew that I was like seething.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: silently.
Codey: Um, but I wasn't gonna, like, I'm not the kind of person to just be like, like, shush someone, like, like, I'm like, I'm gonna go over and just say, like, hey, heads up, like, you are just disturbing.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Yeah, and like, honestly, like, I think that's the best way because I would also want somebody to tell me, like, I've been in a position where I'm talking and not realising.
Codey: Oh yeah.
Kelly: Like, you know, I think just go over and say, like, um, can you please be quiet?
Kelly: Like, that's, I don't think I've ever once been like, no, I'm gonna talk louder, actually.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: No, actually.
Codey: Yeah, that's nuts.
Codey: So that's what we've been up to.
Codey: Um, okay, so moving on to uh, Cody's Entomology Corner.
Codey: So I always start this off with questions and Kelly has decided that we're going to talk, she's going to ask her questions like in the middle of like while the episode's going like as things come up, which is great.
Codey: But in the Slack, there were a couple of really good questions.
Codey: So Stuart, for example, has a question and he said, what are the thoughts about collecting bugs?
Codey: Cody talked about nets and pins and stuff, which obviously means the bugs are going to be quite dead after.
Codey: Is the general opinion that, is the general opinion that that's okay.
Codey: I'm fascinated by big Victorian entomology cases, but they're not exactly in wide supply.
Codey: Are we good to make our own collections?
Codey: And he said, not that we have any super exciting bugs from a display point of view.
Codey: Um, where it's from.
Codey: And another person on Slack Ryan said, so basically, is it cool to kill bugs and display their carcasses?
Kelly: Which I like both these questions because I also love the uh, Victorian display cases and like, also just like, all of the displays.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, I have looked into a few classes by me.
Kelly: Um, but I'm sure you're going to talk about it, but like, it's all about, um, like ethical, Harvesting, right, of the bugs?
Codey: Mm.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Correct.
Kelly: Yeah, okay.
Kelly: Because that's like with every animal.
Kelly: Like I also like taxidermy.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And like that can be so questionable.
Codey: Yeah, it really depends on
Codey: Yeah, like, it depends on how you are harvesting them.
Codey: Like, if you are just out there, like, with a taxidermy, like if you're out there with a gun just like killing all of the lions so that you can taxidermy them, not great.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And we had a whole period of time where we did this a lot. And then people were like, wait a minute, this is not great because, like, organisms like the Tasmanian tiger, um, or Tasmanian wolf, like, I can't remember exactly what it was called, but that was something that was hunted to extinction.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: There are other, there are many other animals that have been hunted to extinction because people want to have a big shiny display or like taxidermy or whatever.
Codey: So, um, yeah, it's a really good question, especially, so this is something that we have, we talk about quite a lot in, um, entomology and it's something that is still continuing to be discussed because in most research avenues, uh, if you are working with vertebrate animals and and some fish, you have to have like specific, you have to go through a specific and rigourous,
Codey: protocol to make sure that like, to prove before you even do your research, that you're going to take care of these animals, that they're going to be in good health, that if you do have to euthanize them as part of your project, you are going to do so humanely.
Codey: Like, you have to basically step by step, prove, um, to the researching body at whatever institution that you're at, that like, you are going to take the appropriate steps.
Codey: Um, that does not exist for both.
Codey: It does not exist.
Kelly: Oh.
Kelly: I was gonna say, that's so reassuring for animals, I guess, because there's definitely been so many cases of abuse in that regard.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, but, uh, the bugs for bugs.
Codey: The, so yeah, invertebrates are not something that is uh, within that realm.
Codey: Um, I mean, part of that is like, we don't have a good understanding of, like, their, you know, pain, like, how do we know when they're in pain or how do we know?
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like, we don't have a very good understanding of that.
Codey: So it's, it's a little difficult to create standards, if we don't have that information.
Codey: And it's going to be highly dependent, you know, based on what you're studying.
Codey: However, there are a lot of entomologists, myself included, that think that before you do anything, I do a lot of collecting.
Codey: And I make sure that whenever I do any collections, I seriously consider what am I going to do with my bugs?
Codey: Like what, after I collect all these data and then I can say things about, you know, where I caught things, how I caught things, et cetera, et cetera, what's going to happen to all of these insects?
Codey: And not only the ones that I'm interested in studying, but also the ones that are caught as a consequence of it.
Codey: So like think of someone who's fishing and they throw a net and they catch all of these fish that they're that are part of their fishery and they're going to sell these fish to their fishery, but they also catch lobsters and sharks.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And like, you know, other things that are not what their target is.
Codey: And that happens a lot in insect research as well.
Codey: So we put traps out like for bees, but these traps don't just collect bees.
Codey: It's not, you know, it's not like these traps are sitting in the environment and if a beetle comes around, the trap is like, no, you are not chosen.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So it's something that not a lot of peop, not a lot of people have considered, but it's becoming more common to start thinking about the ethical ramifications of our capture.
Codey: I think the general consensus is that it's not, it doesn't harm the environment.
Codey: As long as you don't have those traps out, like in perpetuity, constantly running.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So a lot of us will do just snapshots.
Codey: So I would put traps out for maybe a week or maybe like a couple days and I would only have so many traps in the in the area so that I could make the inferences that I want to make from that information.
Codey: But I won't like just have it in every square inch of, like, I won't have traps everywhere.
Codey: So, even if you are impacting the population at the area that your trap is, there's still like so much more forest.
Codey: There's so much more whatever your habitat is that you are not touching.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: It's almost kind of even like mushroom collecting.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Where, you know, like people are only supposed to harvest, um, like a section of wild mushrooms that like the rest can continue growing and they're not like just wiping out, uh, an entire area of those mushrooms, um,
Kelly: But I think that's like a really good approach, like that's, that seems like so, um, I can't even think of that, like, oh, uh, conscious, I guess.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Um, so there's that aspect of it where you consider where you're going to put your traps.
Codey: Also, depending on where you are.
Codey: So, If you're in the Midwest, for example, there are some bumblebee species that are considered either endangered or threatened, including the rusty patch bumblebee.
Codey: And so you actually cannot deploy traps that are indiscriminate.
Codey: It is illegal to do so in for a great amount of that area.
Codey: And so you have to completely change your methodology of how you collect these insects.
Codey: So some people will have nets.
Codey: They might, you know, there are these vacuums, like think of like a handheld vacuum that you would like vacuum out your car with.
Codey: We can actually like literally just hack those apart and make something that you can catch bugs with.
Codey: And that's some of my research was that.
Codey: I just stood over flowers that I planted in a few different arrangements and at different sites and then went to those sites and just caught all of the bugs that were on a certain flower species. And I was basically like, were the insects that visited these flowers different in these different environments.
Codey: Um, And so it's just straight up a vacuum.
Codey: Um, But yeah, so there's, and when we, when we euthanize them as well, we try and do so, um, humanely and ethically is like, we're not just going to let them sit there and just slowly like die in a jar, right?
Codey: Like you, we either freeze them or we, um, put them in a container that has ethylacetate, um, and it, they just slowly kind of go to sleep.
Codey: Um, I usually just recommend the freezer or I will like bring a freezer with me to, um, to the field, like a, like dry ice or something like that.
Codey: I really like dry ice. As an example.
Codey: Um, so it's, it's, it's kind of an, it depends question.
Codey: If you are and it depends on like why you are doing what you're doing.
Codey: So if it's for scientific research, you know, it's generally considered okay.
Codey: But then even within that community, like what are you doing with your bycatch, what are you doing with the bugs once you're done?
Codey: Like, are you just literally like, oh, I studied them all?
Codey: I'm going to toss them in the trash. Or, do you have plans to donate them to an institution in your area?
Codey: Um, like all of the bugs that I collected for my research here at Penn State are going into the Frost Entomological Museum at Penn State.
Codey: So they will be there in perpetuity and can be used further, um, future research.
Codey: Um, and then going to places like I've gone to a couple of things like Beetle school in Arizona and fly school in Costa Rica and there are people that go on those and just kind of are collecting everything that they can because they just and that's, you know, fine as long as they're not collecting every single thing.
Codey: you know?
Codey: You want to make sure that you're collecting like a representative.
Codey: So there were some of these like bright green, shiny beetles, for example, that were there.
Codey: And a lot of us, we caught like one maybe two.
Codey: But other than that, we just left them, you know?
Codey: Because they're endemic to that area.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: They're not super, super common. Or they used to be, but they're not that common anymore.
Codey: And so you just leave them, um, once you have, however many it is that you want.
Codey: So I took, there were 3 species, and I took one of each species, but then I took an extra one that I gave to, again, my museum.
Codey: Um, because my local museum did not have an example of that.
Codey: So if you're going, if you go somewhere.
Codey: Like, if you're going to go to Mexico where monarchs have their like mass overwintering grounds and you just start like hoovering up monarchs, like, clearly not a good thing.
Codey: But, um, if you, and choosing species that might be more sensitive or also clearly not a good thing.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: But there's some really common butterfly species here that if you were to collect a couple of them, like maybe, I don't know, like 15 of them to make a display, not super, something to be super, super concerned about, um, unless you are one of like 100s of people doing so.
Kelly: Yeah, that's that, I mean, that's always the issue.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Too, um.
Kelly: So what do you think about, like, stuff like, uh, people who take, like, the spotter...
Kelly: Oh my god, a spotted spotted lantern fly.
Kelly: And make like jewellery from the wings.
Kelly: Because, you know, they're on like a kill on site list.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So that is another example of, like, it depends.
Codey: So if you were in, if you were in their native range, that'd probably not be a great thing to do, right?
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Codey: But here where we are, especially in like the New York City area, and now where I am in Pennsylvania, they're starting to make their way.
Codey: Um, Yeah, they, these are insects that are highly damaging to our environment.
Kelly: Oh, no.
Codey: Um, they basically, we, forever ago, we brought over this tree called Tree of Heaven.
Codey: that we thought was cool, and we planted it everywhere because people thought it was cool.
Codey: And then spot and lanternfly came over on a freight ship or something.
Codey: Um, it was actually in Berks County, Pennsylvania, 2014.
Kelly: Yeah, I thought it, you know, it's funny because I, I, when you said, oh, they're coming to Pennsylvania.
Kelly: I was like, I'm pretty sure it started there, but then it's not.
Codey: It did.
Kelly: But it's not as big there.
Codey: No, they didn't move.
Codey: So they were kind of stuck in like the Philly area for a while, and then they slowly started making their way west.
Codey: Um, and because we brought all of these trees, tree of heaven, and they're all over the place, it kind of was like, here's all your food.
Codey: Like we've already, we've already populated all your food, but all of the predators in this environment, all of the like birds that could eat them, things like that, they don't, they have not evolved away to be able to consume spotted lanternfly and like compensate for the toxins.
Kelly: We made your environment for you.
Codey: So, spot and lantern fly when they eat tree of heaven, they sequester these, um, toxic chemicals that then act as like a protection because a bug will or a bird will try and eat it and will be like, ugh, that's gross and spit it out and then that bird will never try and eat another one.
Codey: Um, and in, I think where they're from in Korea, like that, there are predators, both vertebrate and invertebrate predator, like other bugs as well, who are just like, well, we've, we have something in our tummies that's going to break that down.
Codey: And so we don't care at all.
Codey: So, that's an insect that we actually,
Codey: We don't have adequate, like, predators in the environment to counter that.
Codey: So that's why we have to step up as individuals to like take them down. And if you can then make art out of it, that's great.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Right?
Kelly: That's, I think it's like very, like a very cool way to like, Both try to help the environment, even though it feels like we're all trying to kill them as much as possible and it's not really working too well.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: But like, a great like recycle also.
Codey: Yeah, and that's something, yeah.
Kelly: And like the wings are really pretty.
Codey: So that's the frustrating part is they're, they are very pretty.
Codey: Um, and people will be like, oh, these are so cute.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And like even as in their larval stages, like in the, sorry, the nymphal stages, like they have, they, they're black and white spotted and then they have red in them and they're just like, they look, they look really interesting and very like exotic and pretty.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, it just sucks that they do so much damage, especially to uh, rape.
Codey: So, in Northwestern Pennsylvania, there's a big grape, um, like culture, viticulture, I think.
Kelly: Oh, I didn't realise.
Kelly: Yeah, so yeah.
Codey: Yeah, so there's, um, there's a really like large amount of of people up there that have wineries that, um, produce a lot of the wine that is consumed either in the area or I don't know if they send it out or whatever, but it's a pretty big commodity here in Pennsylvania.
Codey: And, um, spotting lantern, I sure do love grape.
Codey: I sure do like really mess up great.
Codey: And so that is something that is not, um, that like we, we're trying to stop the spread so they don't make it there because once they're there, you're kind, we're kind of screwed because it's a huge, huge like food source for them and, and then the grape grape vines are going to really struggle.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So another thing that they're doing, that some scientists are trying to do at the same time is like develop strains of grapes that are a little bit more resilient now that we know, like, Spotify, it's only been here for like 12 years.
Codey: So it's not like we've had years and years and years to try and do this, but they are still trying to figure out ways to mitigate it.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: But that type of capture, um, or just that type of killing, like just killing those insects.
Codey: It's encouraged.
Codey: Um, so it's yet more evidence to the, it depends on what you're killing.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, but one of my big research interests personally is is the bycatch.
Codey: So say that, like, I, I, from throughout my research, I have put out these things called blue vein traps that are used to study bees.
Codey: Um, but pretty, like, from the 1st project, I was like, there's so much more that's caught that is not a B.
Codey: And we don't have a very good understanding of what other insects are collected in those.
Codey: And no one has really taken the time to just sit there and identify that by catch.
Codey: And I did some of that for my dissertation.
Codey: Not only with um, with blue vein traps, but with some other common insect traps.
Codey: And I found rare flies.
Codey: I found range expansions of beetles and ants and a wasp.
Codey: Um, one of my friends studies, uh, some wasps and is like, that's that's probably new.
Codey: Um, some of the people, like there's all, there's these tiny, tiny wasps that people are like, I, we don't know how to collect those and I caught a ton of them in these traps.
Codey: And so these are things that are collected and are probably being collected in how, like all of the research projects that are occurring, uh, monitoring insect populations across the world and people don't even look at it.
Codey: They just, they, they call it.
Codey: so funny because we call it bug soup.
Codey: Because it's literally like we put it in a jar, and it's just a bunch of bugs in ethanol, and it just looks like bug soup, um, and people will set it there and they will, like, say, oh, someone will look at it eventually.
Codey: So I'm hoping in my research to provide a list of like here are the things, other things that are caught, like some of the, I'm not, this isn't even extensive.
Codey: Like this is just my research and some of my colleagues who have given me their by catch.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like, these are the things that have been caught in like the eastern United States as by catch of bee projects or of, um, like beetle surveys. And so if you are an individual that studies these, these groups that are hard to catch, and you don't know how to catch them, maybe go down the hall and ask the bee person at your institution for their by catch because they definitely have by catch.
Codey: Um, and that's like an additional collaboration that can come from bugs that are just sitting there.
Codey: Um, so that's like another way of trying to like make make it more ethical.
Codey: The collection of these insects, like try and improve the efficacy and all of the things that we can learn from these insects that we've already collected.
Codey: They're already there, you know?
Kelly: Yeah, like, why wouldn't you, like, share in that, in that?
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And I think it's just like people just don't know what to say.
Codey: Like they, they'll be like, I don't know, there are some flies in there and some fly people are probably like, yeah, it's probably all those really, really common like common things and who has the time, you know, to go through and check.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: But I am kind of blessed that I'm unemployed.
Codey: Um, I mean.
Kelly: The silver lining to unemployment.
Codey: I mean, I do, I have some small identification jobs, but like other, those aren't going to take a ton of my time.
Codey: And so I'm gonna have other time, and in that time, I can go through some of this bycatch.
Codey: And because I've taken Beatle school and fly school and I was an instructor on the wasp by decorse, like I kind of know what groups are the, we don't catch these very often groups, and I know the people that study those groups.
Codey: So I can be like, hey, I actually caught a ton of these, my narrids, which are called fairy fairy flies, fairy wasps.
Codey: There are these tiny, they are the tiniest, um, insect.
Codey: They are so small.
Codey: And we caught a bunch of them.
Codey: And, you know, I can talk to the people that study my marriage and be like, hey, heads up.
Codey: Like, I caught, you know, 300 of these things.
Codey: One of the things, one of the, so is, one of the things that I caught was, is called, uh, is a fly in the family carnidae.
Codey: And they're bird flies, they're like bird parasoid flies.
Codey: And I looked at the most recent publication about this family.
Codey: And it was someone at the American Museum of Natural History looking at all of the individuals that he could find in the museum and it was like 75 specimens.
Codey: I caught like 300.
Codey: In my research.
Codey: So it's like, Like, and I mean, that's research that I did in the canopy, so I put traps up in the canopy, but there are people putting traps in the canopy, like all, like that is something, something that is being done more and more.
Codey: So it's like, you know, like these are, this is a family that like, they're like, man, it's so rare and like, we don't, it's like, no, actually, I think people just aren't looking at the rest of their stuff.
Codey: Um, so yeah, I don't know how, what all I mean, other than just like writing a checklist publication, that's like, here's all the other cool stuff we found.
Codey: Um, I still have to figure out exactly what I want to do with that information.
Kelly: Mm.
Codey: But I mean, I'm all for sharing it.
Codey: Like, I think I'm going to present at a conference in November about it, but.
Kelly: Oh, that's so cool.
Kelly: It's like, it's like support information or like Bug networking.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, It is, and it's something that, you know, it's not like sexy.
Codey: Like, it's not like, oh, I discovered a new thing that, like, I found a new stick insect species or something like that.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like, I mean, it's possible, but you have to sift through like a lot of dead bugs and your girl loves sifting.
Codey: So
Kelly: So it's perfect.
Kelly: I mean, it's like, it's like the people who put out like free programming and, you know, like stuff like that.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: It's, it doesn't usually get, um, applauded or like, it's not like a thrilling, exciting job, like not sexy like you said.
Kelly: But like, it's a vital to the community.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: So I think that's really important.
Codey: And it.
Kelly: And like really nice for you to do also.
Codey: Yeah, I'm blessed that I'm in a situation where I can do that for a little bit. And I'm hoping that if I get like a publication or 2 out of it, someone will be like, hey, do you want to keep doing this, but like being paid for it through this museum or something, I'll be like, yeah, I would love that actually.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: I mean, that would that would be so sick, yeah.
Codey: So, or like have people that do research.
Codey: Like, some of my friends have already said, like, hey, if we're going to do this study, like, if I gave you the flies, how much money would you want to, like, identify the flies?
Codey: I'm like, well, I can only get them to family right now.
Codey: Like, I can't get them like all the way down.
Codey: But it's like, that's another thing.
Codey: Like, I could just be a contractor of like, send me your stuff and I'll identify it for you. And then hopefully, like, increase the, um, the, the footprint of these bugs that you've already caught.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, well, that was a very long-mended answer to uh, what is the thought of collecting bugs?
Kelly: Well, we covered both questions, right?
Codey: It's true.
Kelly: So.
Codey: Um, so yeah, you can, uh, display their carcasses, just, um, another thing, the, I guess the final thing I'll say is that if you do this, like if you make your own collection and you have your own, like, cases of bugs, make a plan either in your will or in something else for what is going to happen to them when you die.
Codey: So there have been so many entomologists that have passed away, unexpectedly, that we don't know what their wishes were with their bugs.
Codey: Like, we don't know, and their spouses are like, we don't want these.
Codey: Like, please get.
Codey: I've been wanting these out of the house for 50 years.
Codey: Get out of the house.
Codey: And and a lot of people will either just sell it or they'll just trash it and it's just like, no, like some.
Kelly: That's so sad.
Codey: There's like some people's life lifetime of just like going on trips and collecting bugs and it's like, pick either pick like an one institution or pick an institution that you have spoken with and told them your wishes and you have like some form of agreement where it's like, okay, the the insects that are from, um, Africa will go to this African institution and the insects that are from Asia will go to this Asian institution.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So there's like, you can do that where you can pick like where they go.
Codey: Um, but it is something that you kind of have to set up beforehand.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Yeah, we don't have communication with ghosts fully down yet.
Codey: Unfortunately, there's a not a Ouija board for, for that.
Kelly: For lawyers.
Codey: For entomologists and figuring out where we want our bugs.
Codey: Okay, so I will try and speed through these groups then.
Codey: So I've been, uh, over the last few episodes, I've been like going over the order level of insect, um, groups and and trying to just like blurb them a little bit.
Codey: So I'm going to keep doing that. So last time we talked about wing insects up to and including the group known as Poly Neoptera.
Codey: And this week we're going to discuss perineoptera, which is the last, like, group, uh, last of the groups except for Hollow Metabola, which is like the big, a really big group and has overwhelmingly the most diversity of, um, insects.
Codey: And I'm going to talk a little bit about those, but then cover some of the hard hitters in the last episode.
Codey: Um, so Perineoptera, uh, I loved this on Wikipedia.
Codey: So I just like took it straight out.
Codey: Perineoptera are just all of the insects classified, uh, that are classified here in exhibit various reductions or simplifications from the primitive body plan found in polyneoptera.
Codey: So again, this is a junk drawer.
Codey: Like.
Codey: If you, if you don't fall into this other category that is the shiny like clear category, you're going to fall over here.
Codey: And that's that's kind of where we are at, I think, with, um, understanding where these things fit in.
Codey: So these include, um, 3 orders, uh, the lice, the thrips, and then the hemipterons or the true bugs, um, which, like, is a big contention about like what the word bug means.
Codey: I'll talk about that when I get to that point.
Codey: So the order Sicodia has the Barclays, the book lice, and the parasitic lice.
Codey: So real close, the real quick, the bark lice are really important decomposers.
Codey: They break down things that other that like are pretty weird, like fungi and algae and lichen.
Codey: So these are things that other organisms aren't are not going to be interested in because a lot of other organisms, um, like plant material or like other animal material, but, um, the bark lice are really good at those other weird things.
Codey: Book lice are called book lice because we 1st found them eating the bindings of old books.
Codey: So they are a little different, um, physically, but basically they really like that kind of like old glue stuff.
Codey: Um, but they also have some decomposing ability in in the wild because they don't just exist with books.
Codey: They just really like books.
Codey: And then the big group is the parasitic lice.
Codey: Kelly, do you see that word?
Kelly: Yes, I.
Codey: Do you want to try and say that word?
Kelly: Um, is it Theraptera?
Codey: So close on the end.
Codey: So this, I hate this every time, I have to say this.
Kelly: Can I just say it's a PHTH, which is crazy.
Codey: It's P. Correct.
Codey: It starts with PHTH, which you basically just make those 2 sounds.
Codey: So it's faptura, like, or sorry, faptura, thaptura.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Theraptura?
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: But you have to make both of those sounds.
Codey: is so stupid, but I think, um, the PHTH IR mean is like, uh, is just like the old English word or the Greek maybe word for louse.
Codey: So this literally just is like lice, uh, wingless lice is what this group is, um, and they aren't always wingless, but we normally find them when they're wingless.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: Um, like individuals might, these are, they're going to be the parasitic lice.
Codey: And they might have wings to move between hosts, like, say, not between hosts necessarily, to find a host.
Codey: So if one louse is on like one body and then it needs to move to another body, like, in the next generation might have might have wings and might move, but then they will drop their wings and then they won't move anymore.
Codey: So there's a couple groups that have that kind of life history where they might give birth, not give birth, they might like have young that are winged, but then those wings don't last.
Codey: Like they will throw them off once they find a good host.
Codey: Um, Parasitic lice are obligate, parasites, so they rely on other organisms to live in consuming other organisms, usually like the blood of other organisms.
Codey: So there's the chewing lice, um, which they will live um, in your hair and feather, the hair and the feathers of whatever the host is, and they'll feed on the skin and the debris.
Codey: Whereas the sucking lice will actually pierce your skin and will feed on your blood or other secretions.
Codey: Um, Yeah.
Codey: So there are like, I can't remember.
Codey: I think head lice are a chewing louse.
Kelly: Okay, that's what I, I was gonna say, that is chewing lace, right?
Codey: So like, I don't,
Codey: Yeah, I don't think that they like suck our blood, but they will consume our like dead hair, whatever, and what, like that kind of stuff, but not fun.
Kelly: Okay.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And, I mean, even just like talking about this, like, I'm sure folks know about headlights and you probably feel like you have lice on your head right now and like you want to scratch your head.
Codey: And unfortunately, there is an entire psychiatric disorder.
Codey: Um, that kind of comes from this and it's called delusory parasitosis or delusional parasitosis.
Codey: So there are, if you take that feeling of like, ah, I have a louse on my head and you just amplify it and make it so that the person truly believes that they are infested with parasites, it becomes a psychiatric disorder.
Codey: Um, and there are a lot of people, um, it's not as uncommon as you'd think.
Codey: Uh, I actually have had a woman email me before saying that she had these bugs that were living on her skin and she hadn't, she hadn't been able to meet her grandchild that had been born last year because she didn't want to infect him with whatever bug she had.
Codey: And she's gone to like, um, dermatologists and some other like doctors and they all have told her that she needs psychiatric help and she's like, so she was basically coming to an entomologist and like, please tell me that like, I'm right and that there are bugs on like crawling on my skin.
Kelly: Oh no.
Codey: And it's just like, oh, like,
Kelly: Ugh.
Codey: And I was able to shift it to someone else.
Codey: Um, but like it, that is something that genuinely happens and people that have that have to have psychiatric help to overcome that belief that they are invested.
Kelly: That's good.
Codey: Um, and I think, yeah, I just wanted to mention that because I think it's, I think it's interesting and it can be incredibly sad.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, but something that happens with uh, that kind of, that kind of thing.
Kelly: There was there was like this case about a woman who, um, it wasn't related to bugs itself, but like she constantly felt like her head was itchy.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And it was, it was like literally just a neurological issue of like there were no,
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: There weren't, there was nothing happening or occurring and like it was just driving her crazy.
Kelly: And like that, ugh.
Kelly: Because, like, I definitely had moments where I've woken up or I felt like I'm covered in bugs and then I have to, like, Check myself and be like, no, there's not a 1000 ticks on you or like fleas on you or something.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, exactly.
Kelly: Um.
Codey: But and a lot of the time it's it's individuals that don't have a lot of understanding of insects or arthropods and so like for like ticks, um, and stuff, like they don't really understand that they're not microscopic.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: You will see them.
Kelly: Exactly, which is like why I think the check is so nice.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: It's like, oh, okay.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: There is nothing there.
Kelly: The only time it's not nice is like the middle of the night when I have to like get up and turn the lights on.
Codey: Right.
Codey: Um, yeah, that's something that's really interesting.
Codey: Um, and not something everyone knows about.
Codey: So, uh, the next order is Thysinotra.
Codey: Um, these are the thrips.
Codey: So this word is similar to fish or this group is similar to fish.
Codey: So like, when you are talking about a fish, singular, you say fish, and then when you're talking about fish plural, you still say fish.
Codey: So this is the same.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: Thrips is the singular and the plural.
Codey: It's not like it's thrips and thrip.
Codey: Like, it's thrips, period.
Codey: So really interesting.
Codey: Um, I'm not entirely sure why we decided to do that uh, in the English language, but whatever.
Codey: So these are mostly pests on plants.
Codey: I love in the Wikipedia article, it said they were cigar shaped, and they really are.
Codey: They're just like two, they're a their tube.
Codey: Um, and they have these really, they have these really like fringe wings, like their wings just are like, look little fringe hairy things, but, um, they're mostly past on plants, but they can also be really good pollinators.
Kelly: They are, yeah.
Codey: People actually think that they might have been one of the 1st pollinator pollinating insects because they go in.
Codey: they're fairly small.
Codey: They will go into the, uh, into the flowers, like inner internal morphology.
Codey: I don't know, the inside of a flower.
Codey: And they might have been like consuming either the nectar or some other plant part, and then they would go to another flower, and that, you know, is indirect, that's a possibility for pollination, and some fossil thrips that have been found have pollen on them, which is nuts.
Codey: Um, The only other thing I like about thrips or that I'll mention about thrips is that they are one of the few examples of asymmetry within insects.
Codey: So the thing about insects, and I guess, like, I guess we're the same as well.
Codey: They're bilaterally symmetrical, right?
Codey: So if you cut us down, like if we're standing and you cut us into one half and another half, like up down, there are, it's like mirror images of them of each other.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: But thrips have asymmetrical mandibles.
Codey: So one of their mandibles is like reduced a lot.
Codey: Another one.
Kelly: Oh, like kind of like crabs?
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Um, so it's really reduced and then the other mandible is still like big.
Codey: And it's, it is just so interesting because it's one of the few examples that we can find of, of something breaking that like bilateral symmetry.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Does it, um, does it help him like, latch onto the plant or is it like?
Codey: Yeah, I think it has to do with their feeding.
Codey: Um, they're feeding style.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: Um, they also, they also, do make this damage on plants that is, uh, is called cat facing damage. Because they say, like, people have said that it looks the damage on the plant looks like a cat's face.
Codey: But I looked at a ton of photos and I didn't, I'm like, I can't, I don't know what people were seeing.
Kelly: I was about to say, I've never heard that, but I did have an issue with them on a plant and it did not look like a cat's face.
Codey: Yeah, it's yeah, they.
Kelly: I don't know about that one.
Codey: I don't, but I, that's just one of those things like, when I've, I have competed in some trivia, like bug trivia things, and like that's like, they'll be like, oh, what kind of instruct makes catfacing damage, or like, what kind of damage does thrips do?
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And, um,
Codey: It's just like, I don't, like, it says this, but I don't know what kind of cats people were looking at when they named it that, but it was not good.
Codey: Uh, okay, the last perineopteran group, uh, order is hemiptera.
Codey: Uh, this means half winged, so Hemi, and then Ptera.
Codey: And this includes the true bugs, and then things like cicadas, leaf hoppers, aphids are in here.
Codey: Um, just that kind of like a lot of plant pests that you'd think of, um, are in this group.
Codey: The defining feature of them is that they have a beak, um, or what's called a rostrum, and it's that all of their mouth parts instead of having mandibles or, um, like a tongue or whatever.
Codey: They just have like a pokey bit and they just jam that thing into the plant.
Codey: Um, and have like, The, they jam that thing into a plant and then they have enzymes that come out of their salivary glands and just like liquify the plant and then they just suck it up.
Kelly: Is it like, uh, sorry, go on.
Codey: Um, unless they are, like, they also might feed on either the xylom or the floam of the plant and so they'll find, they'll like find those, um, things, but they basically have a stabby bit, but they won't stab people because unless you really mess with them because that's not.
Codey: It's not a defence thing.
Codey: It's not a weapon.
Codey: It's literally just their mouth.
Kelly: So is it like um, the little mouth that comes out in alien?
Kelly: Like inside of them, inside their mouth or is it?
Codey: Um, I mean, yeah, as long, if it was a straw, basically.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, like not like fully protruding, you know, I'm sure as far as that either, but similar concept.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, they just have, it's just like a little lance that comes out of their, out of their face at some point in their face.
Codey: And it's, it's really funny because a lot of these, there's 4 what are called suborders within hemiptera, and 3 of them end in Rinca, which is means snout.
Codey: And it's basically just saying the 1st part of the word is basically just saying where their snout comes from, comes out of their body.
Codey: Um, I didn't know that 100% until I was researching for this episode.
Codey: I was like, what is the etymology of this word?
Codey: And then I was like, oh, interesting.
Codey: Um, so like the 1st group, the 1st um, or sub-order is UCanarinka, or Auchanarinka.
Codey: There's a lot of ways that you can, people should look up how to spell these things because the pronunciation is always is wild.
Codey: And it literally just means throat snout.
Codey: And it's basically because the mouth part comes out like down by basically like a their chin area.
Codey: Um, like on their face.
Codey: Their phase is held downwards and then it comes, their their ross room comes out from like their chin, throat, neck area.
Codey: Um, and this includes, this group includes things like cicadas, leaf hoppers and spittle bugs.
Codey: Um, And a lot of these things, uh, communicate through sounds or vibrations.
Codey: Of course, we know cicadas are incredibly freaking loud.
Codey: Um, I think people, scientists have found, like studied it and said that it's the equivalent of if we were standing next to a cannonball when a cannonball goes off.
Codey: Um, that's how loud their sounds are, but something about their temp, their sound producing organ and the way that they quote unquote here.
Codey: Basically, like, there's like a mechanism in there that like stops their ears while they're screaming and then it kind of like goes, like opens again when they're silent.
Codey: And it's it's just super wild.
Kelly: Oh, that's cool.
Codey: Um, But yeah, cicadas are, or the song, song of summer for many people.
Codey: You're hearing a lot of cicadas right now.
Kelly: Um, so it's funny because I actually don't get them a lot by me.
Codey: Mm.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: We get a few.
Kelly: We had like a big brood a few years ago.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: But like growing up.
Kelly: Um, where I lived growing up, all you heard all summer long.
Kelly: Was the sound of cicadas.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like that's that's the sound of summer.
Codey: Yeah, they're they're here as well.
Codey: Um, I guess that's one thing I could mention about cicada specifically, is they have 2 different, um, there's the annual cicadas, so those are ones that come out every single year.
Codey: So they have their young, they're young, burrow underground, and then come up the next year and sing the song of their people and runs repeat.
Codey: But there are also these, um, some species that are known as periodical cicados.
Codey: And these have either a 13 or a 17 year cycle where every 13 years or 17 years they will just come up and and do at like all all of them at the same time.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: basically, like of that brood.
Codey: But there are multiple broods.
Codey: So, like one year there might be one, one brood, and we've tracked them all.
Codey: So it's like brood 10, brewed 12, brewed, whatever.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, And we, it's just so interesting that they have this life history strategy of basically all come out and be loud and do everything and there's so many of us that predators will eat their fill.
Codey: And both.
Kelly: And we'll still have plenty of us left, yeah.
Codey: And there's still so many of us left.
Codey: And the reason that they have either 13 or 17 years is to overcome, like, like a predator cannot evolve to, like, learn that, you know?
Codey: So there are some things that will have like one year off and then they'll come back the next year and they're a predator might like co-evolve with them and have and like learn the same thing.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: So then that predator will be really abundant the year that they're there and then not abundant and then look, they'll come back.
Codey: But with 13 and 17 years, like they, they cannot do that.
Codey: Like your predators will not come back.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, And so it's just the, the,
Kelly: Yeah, I think the 17 year one was the one that just happened a few years.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And it's why, I mean, there, there's just so many, like, it, there everywhere.
Kelly: Oh yeah, it's crazy.
Codey: Like, you can't, you can step on them.
Kelly: And they're they're blind, right?
Kelly: They like can't see well, right? As far as I.
Codey: They they cannot see well.
Codey: They also come out, um, the adult cicadas, I believe all do not have mouth parts.
Codey: So they don't eat.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: They just, they're they're underground.
Codey: They eat in their um, larval state. Uh, or their nympho state and they'll just eat and consume and and wait and bide their time.
Kelly: Yeah, no, because when I was a kid, you'd like be riding your bike at night.
Codey: Oh, and they're hitting you.
Kelly: Oh my god, they'd be hitting you and like you're trying to dodge them, but like they're, they can't see and like they're just flying around.
Codey: Yeah, they don't.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Uh, it was.
Kelly: That was always the least fun part.
Kelly: Because they're so big.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, they're incredibly clumsy flyers, so they are not able to like dodge very well.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Um, But it, this life history strategy, it has been really important for some indigenous tribes.
Codey: So there are some tribes that talk about, like, when here in North America, when Europeans and other colonisers came to overtake the land, some of the people were, like, pushed out off of like their area of where they had food growing or like they weren't allowed to hunt some of their, like, the big game that they usually hunt, like, the colonists would specifically, like, stop them from doing all of that.
Codey: And then, like one of the tribes had that situation going on and they were like almost dying, but then it was a cicada year and like one of the periodical cicadas like came out and they basically were able to survive because and they called it like, they said like it came from like a deity, gave it, gave them the cicadas.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, because it was, it basically, it completely saved their lives.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Kelly: That's so cool.
Codey: So really cool that they have that, uh, the periodical ones are just wild.
Codey: And you can actually track because we have really good understanding of where they are geographically, but also when they're going to come out.
Codey: So if you are in North America,
Codey: You can look, and I mean, I guess other places as well probably have periodical skaters.
Codey: But you should be able, there should be some resource that you could go to
Codey: that's like, here is my geographical location and this is what year it is.
Codey: Like, when's the next time we're going to have a giant cicada boom.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Yeah, because because I remember like the news was like reporting on the 17 year one well in advance before. It actually came out.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: Yeah, it's basically like heads up.
Codey: is happening this year.
Kelly: Yeah, don't freak out.
Codey: Um, and there's a couple areas where, like, you will get a 13 and a 17 at the same time.
Codey: It's just, it doesn't happen often, but it's like, you know, Gert.
Kelly: Oh man.
Kelly: It's like a subway series, like we're just gonna, we're gonna fight each other for all of the resources, but also like maybe because there's so many more muscles survive.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, I don't.
Codey: Well, so I don't know if they have.
Codey: I don't know how much of competition for resources they have underground.
Codey: So I think they mostly consume like roots and stuff.
Kelly: Oh, right, because yeah, they're not going to eat.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: But yeah, absolutely wild.
Codey: Okay, I'm going to move on.
Codey: Um, the next suborder is coleorinca.
Codey: Um, some people say seal ringa.
Codey: I don't always remember.
Codey: Um, so this, I'm just going to breeze over these because I don't know about these.
Codey: They're called moss bugs.
Codey: All of them are flightless and they live in really damp moss habitats and they're all associated with the distribution of a specific tree in Australia, New Zealand.
Codey: New Caledonia and South America.
Codey: Um, and it basically all of those countries used to be continents used to be part of the supercontinent Gondwana.
Codey: Um, and the moss bugs like evolved when those were all connected.
Codey: And then when they all split apart.
Codey: There's just moss bugs in those areas.
Codey: But that's it.
Codey: like just those areas.
Codey: So I have not seen one of these.
Codey: I don't expect to see one ever.
Codey: I mean, I would love.
Kelly: That's that's so interesting though.
Codey: Honestly, I would love to go to New Zealand.
Codey: New Zealand, in Australia, I have such interesting bugs.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Codey: Like, every time I'm at a bug class.
Codey: There's like a whole, if we, if we're covering like 160 families that are endemic to North America.
Codey: There will be like another 30 to 50 families that it's like, oh, and we'll just mention that these exist, but that you're not going to see them unless you're in New Zealand or Arizona.
Codey: Or sorry, Australia, not Arizona.
Kelly: Oh my god, their shells are so cool looking.
Codey: Yes, they have very intricate, um, like,
Kelly: It reminds me of like rice patties or like kind of like the Yellowstone Pools almost.
Codey: Yeah, they there's this really interesting shape.
Codey: I, maybe I'll mention when we get to Heteroptera, um, some other, another family that is kind of cool like that.
Codey: Um, that I like.
Codey: But I will jump to Sternarinka.
Codey: So these are, this means chest snout, so sternum, and then rink a snout.
Codey: And this is because their mouth parts literally look like they're coming out of the middle of their chest.
Codey: So there are some some groups that I'm like, oh, is this a louse?
Codey: Is this like a barc lice or is this a solid?
Codey: And I will just look and if their mouth parts are coming out, it like literally in between their the 1st pair of their legs.
Codey: It's just like there's like a little, a little like boob coming out and it's just like, oh, okay, it's a silly.
Codey: Because otherwise some of these things look very, very similar to some of the Yukon Rankins.
Codey: Um, or sorry, some of the uh, the lice, the cicodians.
Codey: So, really interesting.
Codey: This also includes aphids, white flies, silids, and scale insects, which are,
Kelly: Those last 2 are my nemesis.
Codey: Yes, so, um, silids, scaling sex, and aphids, uh, are all Wi-Fi is to a lesser extent, but these are all things that are incredibly hard-hitting economic damage.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Like, entire crops.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like there is currently a bunch of aphids and silids.
Codey: And I think scale insects down in Florida that are devastating the citrus crop.
Codey: And it's pretty much like, say, like enjoy limes and lemons and oranges while you can because like they are, these things are just going gangbusters down there.
Kelly: Oh no.
Codey: Um, and I know, it sucks.
Kelly: But I love my citrus fruits.
Kelly: I mean, we don't even have good peaches this year because of, um, how hard jersey got hit, but that's not bug related.
Codey: Oh, I mean.
Kelly: That's different.
Codey: Yeah, but it's just they're not some some not fun ones here for sure.
Kelly: And like there's, there's some of them are so hard to get rid of, like, I can't even imagine it on a commercial level.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, scaly sex basically are just, they just look like, they're called that because they just can flatten themselves up against the bark of a tree, and then they look like the bark of the tree.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So it's like, they just camouflage themselves and just live their own little lives with this like hardened back shield thing.
Codey: Um, I've only really ever seen them in their like younger states like that I'm able to really identify in their younger states when they don't have that giant like back piece that is protecting them.
Codey: So they're,
Kelly: Yeah, I feel like it's, it's only more noticeable if there's like a large collection of them in a spot.
Codey: Yeah, because they'll they'll congregate, yeah, in one spot.
Kelly: Yeah, or like, um.
Kelly: They do leave certain markings on leaves, but like, once you get to that point, it's like, okay, now I have to decontaminate an entire plant and hope that I don't miss a single one.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yes, because if you miss a single one, like, it's something's gonna happen, like, it's probably the female that's able to just, like, boom again.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and I will say these, this group, uh, I mean, any of these in these insects, but specifically starting ring ins.
Codey: It's not only that they do, they consume so much of a plant.
Codey: They also have a lot of like viruses that are co-evolved with them and will live inside of them, like in their salivary glands that they will then transmit between plants.
Codey: Um, and the plant, and the, it might be that the disease is what's killing your plant, not necessarily the actual, like herbivary.
Kelly: I didn't know that part, that's.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: That's so cool.
Kelly: I mean, awful, but like, In a really interesting way.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So a lot of, um, there's a good amount, like if, it sucks because I'm, my, my research is in like conservation and biodiversity, but if I switched to pest work, I could get a job so easy because there's so much research being done on pest insects and how to mitigate them, how to, how to like eradicate a specific pest without just destroying all of the other insects in your area.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, it's just a huge field and all of the ag, uh, there's a lot of money in it as well because there's a lot of incentive from agricultural partners, but also like the government to, um, learn how and figure out how to stop the.
Codey: I stop these things from spreading and stop whatever damage or diseases they bring.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Oh, actually, I wanted to ask this.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Is this why?
Kelly: Because I saw in the news, like, uh, 2 days ago or something that like, somebody, Google or somebody wants to release, uh, like a ton of bugs to, I think, mitigate a certain problem, but I think they're an invasive species, species.
Codey: Yeah, so I don't know exactly what you're talking about, but there's a couple different things that people will do so that we do.
Kelly: Because I know they do like the mosquitoes, um, they release the male mosquitoes that are sterile to reduce.
Codey: So.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: Yeah, so that's called that's the sterile insect technique.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: So that's when you, yeah, release a bunch of males that are sterile and they're basically just shooting blanks and they don't know.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And then, like, a lot of insects, once they copulate, they might put in what's called a copulatory plug.
Codey: So like a male might mate with a female and then that's it.
Codey: Like she can't mate again because there's like something physically barring another mating attempt.
Codey: Um, and then it's great if he was sterile.
Codey: Uh, so for some, so that's one thing, but there's also some places, we try not to do this as much, but some places will release predators of something or, um, like parasitoids.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: I feel like that's what it was, but now I can't find it.
Kelly: So I don't know if I was...
Codey: Yeah, so it was probably the biological control side of it.
Codey: So that's usually it's gonna, it's often a parasitoid wasp.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: So, um, it's usually a parasoid wasp species or or whatever that might be local but might not be, but they're usually so well adapted and like to their specific host that people will release that wasp.
Codey: Like they'll breed up a ton of those wasps and then release them and then the females will lay their egg in the, um, other insect and then their egg will grow and like will basically just decimate whatever that insect is.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and then once the like, this is done a lot with aphids.
Codey: And then once the aphids are gone, that wasp just kind of also dies out because, yeah.
Kelly: Disappears with it.
Kelly: That's actually real.
Kelly: I didn't know that that was, um, a process that we had.
Kelly: That one sounds really cool also, because we've had good success with the mosquito sterilisation in the past, right?
Codey: Well, so there's.
Codey: Yeah, the issue with biological control is you can never be 100% sure that that insect is not like whatever you release as the control agent is not going to be able to adapt to a different organism.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So it could be that like you, I mean, it's one of those things like if it's a, uh, a wasp that parasitises aphids and then it adapts and suddenly compariasitize another aphid, like we're not going to cry because it's an aphid.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Codey: But it.
Kelly: That's that's the best case scenario.
Codey: But there are some things that like are more generalist.
Codey: Um, so we usually don't choose those for biological control, but it's, you're never sure, like if there's always going to be exceptions.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: So it could be that you release something and it only does this one AFID, but then in the environment, there's also this B, this does not happen, but head, just like as an example.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: There's also this bee that somehow it can parasitise as well.
Codey: And then now you have released something that is going to devastate, like something that you actually, that is beneficial that you care about, that was unintended consequence.
Codey: Um,
Codey: And this is, there's some really bad stories of this with like vertebrates.
Kelly: I was going to say, um, in the time where I grew up, they released frogs.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: To get rid of the mosquitoes or control the mosquitoes and then there were a abundance of frogs that were just eating everything and then I think they caused more raccoons to come and also then people released cats.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Mhm.
Kelly: Or something to control the fraud.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: Like, it was just, Clearly chaos going down the line and nobody was catching on that like releasing these animals was not helping the process.
Codey: Yeah, um, another example is the cane toad.
Codey: And I'm trying to remember exactly what that all was about.
Kelly: Yes.
Codey: Um, it was introduced.
Kelly: I remember that mess, but I can't remember.
Codey: Yeah, so the cane toad has been introduced to many regions of the world for the biological control of agricultural past.
Codey: So yeah, similar.
Codey: Um, it was released to get rid of a pest.
Codey: And then, um,
Codey: It just kind of went gangbusters.
Codey: Uh, so it's, so this is, as a result, 102 toads were collected from Hawaii and brought to Australia.
Codey: So it started with 102.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Codey: Um, it is much more than that now.
Codey: Um, and they have been, uh, so that I'm seeing that they have been, the cane toad has been linked to the decrease of uh, an organism called the quals, northern quals.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: It's like a it's a marsupial, I'm assuming.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Codey: So it's like one of those things like, oh, this is going to be a great idea.
Codey: And then it's like, oh, heck, that was not actually a great idea.
Codey: These unintended consequences.
Codey: So it's possible that something was released as biological control that you saw because that is happening fairly regularly as well.
Codey: Um, the last order before we, I'd go over some of the holo metabolist organisms is heteroptera.
Codey: So these are the true true bugs.
Codey: So legitimately true bugs.
Codey: So when when we 1st when entomologists 1st started, I think this is what we were what we meant when we said bug.
Codey: is these things.
Codey: So these are now what's called the true bugs.
Codey: But of course, people just refer to all insects as bugs.
Codey: And I feel like every young entomologist has a stage in their life where they're really, really grumpy about people calling, referring to insects or even spiders or whatever, like as bugs.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Because you're like, no, Bugs is actually just Tanoraptura.
Codey: Um, I have I have gotten past that point in my life because I don't think that it really matters.
Codey: It doesn't.
Kelly: I think that's fair.
Kelly: I think I think that's also like a thing that like just most people go through in life where like the thing that they like really enjoy.
Kelly: You know, it gets talked about by somebody who is using terms that they don't fully understand or.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And then you get frustrated.
Kelly: You know, I think I think that's something most people can, but like for you, especially it has to be worse.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: Yeah, there's so much misinformation.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: But I do have a question because you said these are the junk draw bugs, right?
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Oh, so the, it's the perineoptera is the drunk drawer of the bugs.
Kelly: Oh, okay, because, because I was gonna ask, like, that's kind of messed up that they're considered true bugs, but then thrown in the drug draw.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: No, no, no.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: These are, these are, these are pretty distinctly like their own little, little things, so.
Kelly: That's what I was kind of confused because like they seem like bugs that can be classified.
Kelly: Yeah, okay.
Codey: Yes, yes, 100%.
Codey: Um, so some common families, um, some of the common names of families that you would probably uh, recognise are things like stink bugs, bag bugs, pirate bugs, assassin bugs, giant water bugs, um, these are all within heteroptera.
Codey: Um, I wanted to shout out 2 things.
Codey: So 1st of all, there's the family Tingiday or Tingiday, which are the lace bugs.
Codey: And I wanted to mention these because you were appreciating how the Colia Rinkin's look.
Kelly: Yes, I, I literally, so, because it's funny because I was looking up, For this also, because not to jump ahead, but like there is a lace bug in silk song. But I don't think there, that's who lace is based off of, um, Which is funny because it's like, uh, there's a few misnomers, I think, in the game.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: No.
Kelly: In that regard.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: But yeah, lace bugs are so pretty. And I definitely see the connection that you made with the early...
Codey: Yeah, so lace bugs are just bugs that instead of having like a shield that is like a, like a back end that is very like obviously like their, their back or whatever, like think of like a, uh, stink bug, like you, there's that almost shield like, um, And it's all one colour and you can't see through it.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Lace bugs, it's like someone has just intricately like made that.
Codey: Um, their, uh, what are known as hemulytra.
Codey: These, um, they're not true wings, but like the things that are on their back that kind of like mimic wings or are the, um, the, 0 my gosh, an adapted wing or like a different type of wing, they are, they look like lace.
Codey: Like they look like they're a lace doily.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Literally, it looks like that or like stained glass on some of them, depending on like what fills in in between.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So I, I think these, these things are so cool.
Codey: Um, they are unfortunately also possibly a pest species.
Codey: But they're so pretty.
Kelly: Isn't there, um, I mean, obviously there's pests, but I guess this would be more about like invasive species.
Kelly: Like, I think we've been, there's been like conversations about reconsidering what we consider invasive, invasive species or how we consider them now because of like global trade and everything.
Codey: Yes, yeah.
Codey: Yeah, so there are some organisms that, like, are going to be a pest on a plant, for example, but they won't do enough damage to be, like, fully considered a pest, like, they're, they're, they are, they eat the plant.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: They are an herbivore on that plant, but they haven't quite attained pest status.
Codey: And I think that we're trying to do something similar with the word invasive.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, because, I mean, thinking about it, a lot of these insects, if given, like, if we weren't here to facilitate their movements, they would move, like, they're gonna move around on the environment, if they're, they'll either adapt or, like, the climate will shift a little bit, and so they will move to a different geographic location.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Exactly.
Codey: So, talking about them as invasive is assuming that they belong one place and they are outside of that place.
Codey: Um, And so that is something that like we're trying to think about how to talk about.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And I think my, where I fall is, I would consider something invasive if we facilitated its movement into another area and it is now, like a pest in that area or like a damage, like damaging in that area.
Kelly: Okay, okay, like I agree.
Kelly: I think like, like the lantern flies kind of go with this because like they wouldn't be thriving as much if we hadn't brought the trees over 1st and created that like perfect environment for them.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: So, yeah, okay.
Kelly: That that's that's interesting.
Codey: And like if they had, if they had made their way over here at some point, like they, they would not have come on a ship, right?
Codey: Like they would have had to go like through the proper channels.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: No, they would have like come over like through a land bridge or something geographically in such a way that like, they would have predators that come with them, like, and things that follow them that are also a part of that make it so that when by the time they get here, they can be a fully functioning, like, part of the ecosystem and maybe not damaging.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like they aren't 100% pests where they're, where they are naturally because they have so many like natural predators and stuff.
Codey: Um, But by taking something and putting it into an area where there is like no protection from it.
Codey: And they're just going wild.
Codey: Um, I think personally that can be considered invasive.
Codey: So.
Kelly: No, I think that's like a really cool way to look at it too, and like make sense because like we intervene in such a way that like we skipped the natural order of everything.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: yep.
Codey: There is also, I will say there is a um, sociological standpoint of it as well.
Codey: So a lot of these insects, um, that are considered invasive that are damaging here in North America come from Asia.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And there are people that have equated this to the people that come here as well, that like,
Kelly: Yeah, I've I've definitely seen some like, racism going on within that.
Codey: Yes.
Kelly: Um, unfortunately.
Codey: And so that, I think that's another thing that we need to be be cognisant of when we were speaking about invasive species and about, um, like that kind of thing.
Kelly: Mhm.
Codey: Like, I think because Asia is so the geography, the climate, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, Asia is so vastly different and has just such completely different biodiversity, but is not too different climatically, it allows things, like things that are completely different that, like, our local areas can't handle, like, can come over, um, and can then thrive in this area, but that is very, very different from, like,
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yes.
Codey: a human being coming here and like fitting into the, like, into the society and whatever, you know, it's very, very different.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Codey: And so that's something that we also try and make sure that we, that we, um, are cognisant of when we speak of, you know, species from other, other continents, other areas that we're not saying that things that come from that area are 100% invasive pests, blah, blah, blah, but like,
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah, like they're bad because they're from Asia.
Codey: Yeah, no, no, it's not that.
Kelly: Like, no, that's.
Codey: There's actually, um, there are some tree species that we that we have that are having some issues, whether it's with a fungus or with a, uh, insect or whatever, but we are splicing the DNA of our native tree species with, like, an Asian equivalent that is protected against these things, against these diseases, against these pests.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and creating like a hybrid that is still majority like this hour species, but it provides that protection.
Kelly: Oh, that's cool.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And I think we're trying to save like, I think, the chestnut that way and maybe like something like that.
Kelly: Oh, okay, yeah.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Kelly: That would be awesome.
Kelly: Like that that sounds so cool.
Codey: So it's, Yes.
Codey: Um, the last thing I wanted to mention with Heteroptera is, uh, so the majority of things in this order are herbivorous, but there are some weirdos.
Codey: So like assassin bugs, for example, or ambush bugs.
Codey: Like these things eat other bugs.
Codey: That's what they do.
Codey: Um, but when I was in Hawaii, I learned about this bug called the YQ bug, I think, is how you say this.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and I guess there's a couple species of it, but this the species, specific species that I learned about.
Codey: is one that lives at the summit of Monicaea on the big island.
Codey: So this is a true bug that like, like think of these little tiny things.
Codey: Like think of an aphid.
Codey: It's, I mean, it's not, it's not an aphid.
Kelly: Mhm. And they can survive like, that temperature?
Codey: Correct.
Codey: They have an anti-freeze protein in their chemolymph.
Codey: So they are able to not freeze to death and they live at the top.
Codey: And so they are from a fam, they are from the family Ligeity, which are known as the seed bugs that, for the most part, eat consume seeds.
Codey: However, this specific species.
Codey: has adapted, is adapted to consume the dead bugs that get blown up to the summit of Monica.
Kelly: That's so cool.
Codey: So this is like a bug that you'd think that you'd see it, like as an entomologist, you'd see it, and you'd be like, oh, I wonder what kind of seeds this thing is eating.
Codey: And it's literally just like, if there's like a butterfly that was caught by the wind and blew up to the summit of Mauna Kea and clearly cannot survive up there because it's so, it's like snowy and icy and whatever.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and it dies.
Codey: There's this bug then is like, oh, yum, dinner.
Codey: It's like, what is going on?
Codey: It's just another example of like, you can say these, like these,
Codey: Oh, these are the seed bugs.
Codey: This is what they do 100% and evolution's like, nah.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: No, no, no, no.
Codey: You can't put us in a box.
Kelly: Uh, I wonder, um, I think that has an interesting tie in, actually.
Codey: Yeah, true, true.
Codey: So keep keep that.
Kelly: Right? With like the way, yeah.
Codey: Keep that in mind, the getting blown to a transported.
Kelly: To a cold, high location?
Codey: Yes.
Codey: We'll put a pin in that.
Codey: Okay, um, last thing, hollow metabola.
Codey: So these, this hollow metabola means complete change, so entire like change.
Codey: Everything up until this point has had life stages that include moulting from one form, um, that looks like the next form.
Codey: So think of, you know, like Aphids are like that.
Codey: Um, Sputalantern Pfies are less like that.
Codey: But like some of their nymphal forms like look very, very similar until they get to the adult stage.
Codey: Um, grasshoppers, like a, uh, a young grasshopper that's not sexually mature, looks very, very similar to an adult grasshopper, and they all consume the same thing.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like they they share their the same food source.
Codey: But holo metabolism is when an organism, the insect has an egg, a larva, a pupa, a full pupil stage and then an adult stage.
Codey: These are all distinct from each other.
Codey: And when they are within the larval stage and the adult stage, those are the 2 most, for the most part, feeding, like that's when they're eating, they are eating completely different things.
Codey: So bees, for example, um, They, the adults mostly eat the nectar.
Codey: They'll eat some protein, the females will eat some protein to, sorry, some pollen to get the protein to make their eggs, but then what they leave as a provision for their young is going to be mostly pollen, but it'll have some nectar.
Codey: Another example is butterflies.
Codey: So a butterfly adult that's flying around is consuming nectar, but the young consume the plant material, they'll like consume like the leaves of the plant.
Codey: So this is great.
Codey: Like, if you can have a ton of babies and they don't compete with you for food.
Codey: This is a great, like, life history to have.
Kelly: Mm.
Codey: Um, and it's no wonder then that this group, the hollow metabolist insects are the ones that have the the majority, like almost all of the insect diversity is is here.
Codey: Um, so I'm going to save Diptera, which are the flies, Coleoptera, the Beatles, and the Moths, and Hymenoptera, the Bees, and and Wasps, for the lot for next episode.
Codey: Um, because I really want to go into like specific families for them.
Codey: But I'm going to cover like the other, I think it's like 7 really briefly here.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: Um, and I'm going to say that these are also not listed based on evolutionary relatedness.
Codey: So the 1st one is not related, like as more closely related to the 2nd one than it is, the 3rd one, et cetera, et cetera.
Codey: I'm just kind of going based on vibes.
Codey: Um, Okay, briefly, uh, Raffitioptera are the snake flies, Raffitioptera means needle wing.
Codey: Um, they are just really thin.
Codey: They have super long necks.
Codey: I think that's why they're called snake flies.
Codey: They look like a snake that has that then has like a body and like legs and stuff.
Codey: Um, and they're really interesting and they're not super, super common, but I did catch one in Arizona.
Kelly: Yeah, they look so cool.
Codey: So I have one in my the my one representative of that order in my collection.
Kelly: Oh nice.
Codey: Super cool.
Codey: Um, The next order is Megaloptera.
Codey: So these are the Alderflies and allies is what they say.
Codey: It's basically the alder flies and other things that fit into this group, but it's like hard to like put a name to it.
Codey: Megaloptera just means large wing.
Codey: Mega large wing.
Codey: Um, they have these large clumsy wings, they're really bad flyers, so they are not able to control their flight very well, but they can get around.
Codey: Um, They often have these giant mandibles.
Codey: So Dobson flies are within this group.
Codey: I don't know if you know of Dobson flies.
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: Um, many of them, they will have these giant mandibles that look really, really scary and you're like, 0 my gosh, that thing is going to attack the heck out of me.
Codey: The only reason that they have these is to impress the females.
Codey: They'll also, they might like, fight the other males or something, but it's not something that they're really going to mess with you a lot.
Codey: Um, so it looks scary, but you're fine.
Codey: And the larvae of Dobson flies are known as Helgermites.
Codey: Which I just love that word that it's like, there's this thing from Howell, basically.
Codey: Um, and they're like very large.
Codey: They're aquatic, and they're very large, and people will often like catch these and then use them as bait.
Kelly: I was going to say, I use them as fly fishing baby.
Codey: Yep, yep.
Codey: There are also sometimes called toe biters depending on where you're at.
Codey: Because I think it hurts.
Codey: Have you ever been bitten by one?
Kelly: I was not, luckily.
Codey: Okay.
Codey: But yeah, because the young, definitely like their mandibles are, they have a purpose.
Codey: And they mean business.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, they do.
Kelly: They look like they have a purpose.
Codey: Yeah, for sure.
Codey: Um, the next order is neuroptera, so these are the lace wings, and this just means nerve wing.
Codey: Um, and they're so-called because they just have a ton of veins in their wing.
Codey: And I mentioned in a previous episode that the benefit of having veins in your wing is increased structure, um, because the veins will solidify, uh, and harden and then provide more of a structure for, uh, the memberness, like part of the wing to, uh, help produce flight, um, and drag and stuff.
Codey: And so these just have a ton of veins.
Codey: It's like oops, all veins.
Codey: Um, these, uh, neuropterans, lace wings are super important, uh, as predators of things like aphids, um, not only as adults, but also as heat they're young.
Codey: This order also includes ant lions.
Codey: So these are things that bury themselves in the soil and they have like a pit that go, they like construct a pit.
Codey: So an insect might be like walking past and then it kind of falls into this like pit and then the ant lion will like come up and just like snack, like grab it and then pull it under and eat it.
Codey: I think that has.
Kelly: Are they in Africa or?
Codey: They're here.
Kelly: Oh, are they?
Codey: I think, yeah.
Kelly: Okay.
Codey: I was trying really hard.
Codey: I think I found I found an adult, but I didn't find any larvae.
Codey: I just wanted a photo of the pit.
Codey: Um, when I was in Arizona, but yeah, they're in, they're in North America as well.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: That's so cool.
Codey: I'm not, I'm trying to, maybe, like, they're called ant lines because they make a pit.
Codey: Like, like people used to make lion have lion pits and like you'd fight in them and stuff.
Kelly: Maybe.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Um, So I will say, uh, a fun story about neuropterans.
Codey: This is a great example of even the biggest things can still be a discovery.
Codey: So my advisor, um, was in Arizona and, or sorry, Arkansas. And he was in a Walmart parking lot and he saw this lace wing on the side of a building on the side of the Walmart and he was like, oh, cool.
Codey: And he just caught it in his hand and they're not, they don't bite or anything, but he just like caught it.
Codey: And he went in and like bought milk and whatever else he was there for.
Codey: And then he came back, he came back.
Codey: And that insect, like he just had it down as like a, a brown lace wing, like a the family that includes brown lace wings for a really long time.
Codey: And then while he was teaching like in my class on Zoom, um, during the pandemic, while he was teaching us about it, he pulled out this hit the giant light swing to show us and he was showing it as an example of a Brownlee swing to look at like the veins.
Codey: And we all had like pictures of what the vein, the vein structure of a brown light swing looks like and we're like, mmm, mmm, like, this doesn't, and he was also like, wait, this is, hmm.
Codey: And he kind of like pondered a little bit because his job his whole job is like identifying bugs.
Codey: And it turns out that this was not uh, that family.
Codey: It was this other family that hadn't been seen for like a long time and hadn't been seen that far, like in that geographic area, like ever.
Codey: And so during the, like there was this huge article, and then he was, um, and I was, I was interviewed for the article.
Kelly: Oh, that's so cool.
Codey: So like I am mentioned in this article.
Codey: But then also, like, this was picked up by the New York Times and like all of the big, like BBC, like all of these things.
Codey: And some of my friends were sending me this being like, oh, wow, did you see this article?
Codey: And I'm like, You didn't read it.
Codey: Did you?
Codey: You would know that I saw that article at that time.
Codey: Um, let me see.
Codey: Oh, yeah, I said we were watching what Dr. Scobaro saw under his microscope and he's talking about the features and then just kind of stops.
Codey: We all realised together that the insect was not what it was labelled and was in fact a super rare giant lace wing.
Codey: I still remember the feeling.
Codey: It was so gratifying to know that the excitement doesn't dim. The wonder isn't lost.
Codey: Here we were making a true discovery in the middle of an online lab course.
Codey: That's my claim to fame.
Codey: I was quoted there.
Kelly: That's so cool.
Kelly: I haven't, I haven't, um, opened, so I can read it later after.
Codey: Yeah, it is just super fun.
Codey: Um, And I, like, it was, it was one of those things like the, the pandemic.
Codey: So normally that class is taught in the museum, and in the museum, they have all of these, like, examples.
Codey: So he would never have looked at that, like, because he was trying to look at his personal collection to find examples of all of these families.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So he would never have looked at this if it was not the pandemic and we didn't have to like teach he didn't have to teach over Zoom.
Codey: Um, so it was really interesting, but, Again, like this thing is huge.
Kelly: That is so cool.
Codey: It's not a small thing.
Codey: Like, it's pretty big.
Kelly: That's so crazy too, though, because like, I mean, the lace wings I get are like little green ones.
Codey: Yeah, the, the, yeah, that the green lace things are fairly.
Codey: I mean, they're not tiny, but they're not, they're,
Kelly: No, but they're not like huge looking.
Codey: They're not giant.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Like this thing.
Codey: This thing, like, I think when he was holding it in his hand, like it was like pretty much almost like in his entire, like, hand or whatever.
Codey: I also loved,
Kelly: It looks like a giant dragonfly.
Codey: Yes.
Kelly: Like, you know, like, that's what it reminds me of.
Codey: Yeah, and I also loved, um, I looked at some of the Reddit posts at the time because people like in the article is like, yeah, he grabbed the, he just grabbed it with his hand and kept shopping and like people are like, he what?
Kelly: Could you imagine, though, like you're walking around Walmart and you just see this man carrying like a giant bug in one hand while he's like picking up his milk?
Codey: I can because I've been that person.
Codey: Like, it's just so funny that, like, I'm like, 0 yeah, of course he did.
Codey: Like, he was there.
Codey: He didn't have anything with him to like put it in and he still needed milk.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And so, like, of course, like, he did that, but just looking at the comments and people being like, excuse me?
Codey: We're weird, aren't we?
Codey: Um, yeah.
Kelly: Only a little bit.
Kelly: In a good way.
Codey: The next order are called the stripsypterons.
Codey: These are the twisted wing parasites.
Codey: Um, and their strip sipter means turning around wing.
Codey: Um, and they're called this because their wings are this really weird shape and they kind of fold them up in weird ways.
Codey: Um, they still have, uh, for, so instead of 4 wings and hind wings, like having the 2 so 2 full pairs of wings.
Codey: They have, the front pair of wings has been adapted, like evolutionarily changed to be these like, like it helps them orient.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: I don't I don't really know how to describe it, but like as they're flying.
Codey: So they only fly with their back wings.
Codey: And then this attachment that they have helps them orient while they're in flight.
Codey: And uh, the flies also do this.
Codey: So, uh, little bonus for about flies, flies, uh, diptera, 2 wings, because they have their 4 wings only, and then they have these halt tears, which are these appendages that help them like navigate, uh, and orient during flight and like stay in the right plane of existence.
Codey: Um, but stripsipterans are the opposite.
Codey: So they have their their forewings are the ones that are like evolved to be this like orienteering thing.
Codey: But that's not the only place.
Codey: That's not all.
Codey: They're cool for other reasons as well.
Codey: And the fact that they are endoparasit- parasites of other insects, where it's not that they lay eggs that parasitise the other insects.
Codey: They themselves do.
Codey: So a female will hatch and she'll have wings and she'll fly and find a host.
Codey: And this host could be a bee, a wasp, a cockroach.
Codey: Um, I think some plant hoppers have some, and the female will, go onto the abdomen of the,
Codey: I think it's usually the abdomen.
Codey: That's where I've seen it with wasps that I've seen.
Codey: And she'll burrow in um, in between the, the segments of the abdomen.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And she burrows in and she drops her wings and she attaches and she will then be there for the rest of her life and she'll like consume the haemolymph of the insect.
Codey: Um, and produce eggs.
Codey: Uh, she will, well, before she produces eggs.
Codey: She, um, attaches, she starts consuming haemolymph, and she emits a pheromone that attracts the males, and the males come and mate with her while she is still embedded in the other inside.
Codey: So, like, imagine you have a tick on you.
Codey: in a place like you can't get to it.
Codey: Like, you can't get rid of it.
Codey: And then another tick comes like another tick comes along and like mates with it.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: It's like, come on.
Codey: Leave me alone.
Kelly: It could just single break.
Codey: Um, see, actually, a little bit does the male, the female will come, and the males are always winged.
Codey: Um, and I actually, so I found some female, like when you find a female in, like a trap, for example, it's within another, another bug.
Codey: So all of the ones I've found have been in either wasps or a couple bees, but it's like you're looking at the bee under the microscope later after you've like pinned it and everything.
Codey: And you're like, oh, there's a strep sipter in there.
Codey: Like, there's something sticking out there.
Codey: Um, and it's like, oh, cool, I have a female.
Codey: And the males are pretty uncommon to collect.
Codey: And I have found, I found like maybe 10 in my trap residue, and it was like striking gold.
Codey: Like I was in, I was ecstatic.
Codey: Because I had been looking through like, like, I think I identified 50,000 insects during my project and like, finding these things, I was like a kid at Christmas.
Codey: I was like, this is so cool.
Codey: Like, I have a male strips after it.
Codey: Um, Yeah, I guess that's it.
Codey: They're just not very common.
Codey: Um, to see, because the males just mate and then die.
Codey: That's the life.
Codey: Um, and also really interestingly, they're the most, the thing that they're most closely related to are Beatles.
Codey: wild.
Kelly: Oh.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Not what you'd expect.
Codey: Um, last three.
Codey: Okay, Tricoptera.
Codey: These are the cadisflies.
Codey: Tricoptera just means hairy winged.
Codey: So these are very closely related to butterflies, but butterflies have scaly wings.
Codey: Um, the larvae are aquatic, and people will use them.
Codey: They like make this silk productive case around them to protect themselves and people will raise caddisfly larvae and give them like turquoise and other things that the larvae will then make into its case.
Codey: And it's like a piece of jewellery at the end of it.
Codey: And people will use this and sell the jewellery.
Codey: Like they'll wait for the larvae.
Codey: to leave the case and and become an adult and leave and whatever.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: But then people will sell that as jewellery, which is really cool.
Kelly: So cool.
Codey: I also have a catisfly case that I got in, um, Arizona.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: I saw it and I picked it up and I was like, oh, there's no, there's not a catisfly in here anymore.
Codey: interesting.
Codey: But what I did see is there was a beetle in there.
Codey: So this caddis fly larvae, just grabbed a whole ass beetle.
Codey: I need to.
Codey: take a photo and send it to you.
Codey: It's like put it on the slack because it's just, it's literally just a beetle that's like, that's like stuck.
Codey: And was... No, it just got, it just got silked into and like tied into this, into the case.
Kelly: So did it like eat it or like what?
Kelly: Ah.
Codey: Like it was an aquatic beetle.
Codey: So it's one of the aquatic beetles.
Codey: Like I was catching some of those beetles just existing.
Codey: Um, they're aquatic as adults.
Codey: But it's just stuck.
Kelly: That's so funny.
Codey: Just imagine you're swimming around and someone grabs you and makes you makes you part of their clothing, basically.
Kelly: You're coming home with me.
Codey: Yeah, exactly.
Codey: Oh, so interesting.
Codey: Caddis flies are another one of the groups that are really important for in relation to water quality and they're really important for fly fishing.
Codey: Um, like people will try and make their flies look like a like a caddis fly.
Codey: Um, okay, macoptera.
Codey: So these are the scorpion flies, and they're called that because they look like scorpions.
Codey: So they're really big family is called Panorpidae, and we have these in Pennsylvania.
Codey: So I see them fairly regularly.
Codey: And the adult, it's it's the fact that their hind end is like structure, it looks like a scorpion tail.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And I can't remember if it actually has venom or not, or if it's just used to stab to like.
Kelly: I don't think it is because I've seen these before.
Kelly: Like, I've seen them when I would visit my family in Pennsylvania.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And I remember being horrified.
Kelly: And them just being like, no, you're fine.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like, it's not.
Codey: It's not gonna bother, like, it won't bother you.
Kelly: Not gonna hurt you.
Codey: I don't know
Codey: It might be something that like they fight each other though.
Codey: Like a male fights another male.
Kelly: Maybe, yeah, something like that.
Codey: Because...
Kelly: Also, like they have like freaky faces, right?
Kelly: Like they have like a long nose or something.
Codey: Yes, their faces.
Kelly: Yeah, I know they're like weird all around.
Codey: They they have a lot going on.
Codey: But yeah, they're facing, they have like this really long snoot.
Codey: like think of like an ant eater almost.
Codey: Like, it just, it's just like a long, elongated snoot.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: It's a very interesting bug.
Codey: It is, and the adults are scavengers, so they'll eat dead bugs that they find, including from spider webs.
Codey: So they will actually like take a dead bug out of a spider web and and fly off with it.
Codey: And the spider's like, no, you kids.
Codey: Um, and then the larvae scavenge for other insects, uh, while in the leaf litter.
Codey: So all around, they're just good scavengers.
Codey: But if you haven't, if you've never seen a scorpion fly, look up the family, Panorpid, or we'll put it in the show notes.
Codey: These things are nuts.
Codey: Um, okay, last fam- last order is syphon after us.
Codey: These are the fleas.
Codey: Um, they are also obligate parasites.
Codey: They are flattened sideways.
Codey: I feel like everyone knows what a flea is.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Really not a lot to say.
Codey: I will say, I'm always shocked that these are hollow metabolis because I always, my brain always puts them alongside lice that they're like probably really closely related to lice, but they're not, like, they are...
Kelly: Um, I would have assumed the same thing, honestly, like.
Codey: Yeah, but they are pretty far away, like pretty distinct.
Codey: And it's just this is just another example of organisms converging on a certain body plan or a certain strategy.
Codey: So, um, you know, like there's a couple different.
Codey: There also a fly that did this.
Codey: There's like flies that have become like louse flies that will that look like lice, but it's a fly.
Codey: Um, It's just if there's a niche that exists, a niche that exists.
Codey: can't remember what Johnny hated and what he liked when it.
Codey: How do you say niche or niche?
Kelly: I say niche.
Codey: I think I say niche as well.
Kelly: But both are correct, so.
Codey: Technically, yeah, but one is one is better.
Codey: Um, I like I prefer niche.
Kelly: I think niche is more common as far as I've heard.
Kelly: I also prefer nation.
Codey: Yeah, that, like, you know, there's things that you could suck the blood out of, and there's a certain body plan of being flat that helps you to do that effectively and avoid getting captured.
Codey: And so there's, you know, these that do that, there's lice, there's, um,
Kelly: I mean, you even have like flounders, like, you know, it's a...
Codey: Yeah, yeah.
Codey: Um, yeah, it's just another example of, uh, there's there's a niche and you gotta, it, it behoves you to look a certain way if you're gonna do that.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Okay, I will stop it there.
Codey: We've been talking for a hot minute.
Codey: Um, and now we'll jump into silk saw.
Codey: So yeah, our main topic today is Silk Song, or I guess Hollow Knight Silk song is the whole title of the game. So the quick blurb of this game on Steam and is, quote, discover a vast, haunted kingdom and Holla Knight Silk song, Explorer Fight, and survive as you ascend to the peak of a land ruled by silk and song.
Codey: Um, So this game is a sequel.
Codey: Uh, holiday night itself came out in 2017, and then in 2019, Team Cherry mentioned that there will be, there would be a DLC coming out, and it was called Silk Song.
Codey: Uh, and people just waited.
Codey: They were like drip feeding things, I guess, and there was a...
Kelly: Um, No.
Kelly: There was like communication for like the 1st 2 years and then there was like radio silence.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um, besides like a few comments from their PR guy, uh, let on on Twitter.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, but there was a few moments where I was kind of like, did they die?
Kelly: Like, are they alive at all?
Codey: Okay, 0 no.
Kelly: But also, I had full faith in them?
Kelly: To, to, to come out of this?
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like, I never doubted or their, um, finishing of this game.
Kelly: I guess.
Codey: Yeah, they're just...
Kelly: I think there's a lot of people I would doubt.
Codey: Yeah, you just gotta let them cook.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: Exactly, like, I'm very patient.
Kelly: I'm still waiting for the next Game of Thrones book.
Kelly: You know?
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: I am a very patient person.
Codey: Yeah, so people, people were waiting for a hot minute.
Codey: And then, uh, last year, Team Cherry had said they had a special announcement on August 20, 21st.
Codey: It was like 2 days before.
Codey: They were like, hey, we're gonna have a special live stream on the 21st, like, make sure that you're there.
Codey: And during that live stream or that announcement, they were like, so the game is done and it'll be released in 2 weeks.
Kelly: Yeah, yep.
Codey: From...
Kelly: Which was like kind of like mentally hard for me because like I like to prepare for things and I was like, oh, maybe I'll play hollow night before silk song actually comes out.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, and that definitely wasn't enough time for that.
Kelly: I mean, like, it definitely could have been, but like, I like to take my time.
Kelly: I don't know.
Codey: I mean, it's, there's, there's definitely, you can speed run out.
Codey: There's a bit a healthy speed running community for hollow night and now for silk song.
Kelly: Yes, yeah.
Codey: Um, but there's also just fun.
Codey: It like a cute little story.
Codey: There's a lot more.
Codey: there's like lure to it and stuff.
Codey: So you can just do it as like a speed run fun game, fun like, challenge, but you could, there's also a lot to enjoy if you take your time.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah, there's there, it's a huge world in both games.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And I will say it was really funny because a lot of games moved their release date when Silk Song.
Kelly: Yes.
Kelly: They were like, oh, the king is coming.
Kelly: Let me, or I'm sorry, the queen, I guess, is coming.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Let me step out of the way.
Codey: And I remember like some games.
Codey: And we talked about this on the podcast at the time, but like some games were like, it was like getting out of the way of a whale.
Codey: Like you were just a small grill and you're just like, I need to, I need to let this.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Well, and because if you tried to release again at the same time,
Codey: I feel like a lot of these games will have an overlap.
Codey: A lot of the people that, like, cosy games will overlap with people that like Silk Song, um, and so, like, your take, it's completely detracting from your player base.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And so.
Kelly: I mean, like that, like, uh, just like marketing and like spoken word and like content creators, even like playing your game, like,
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: You know, I think unfortunately that is one thing that like they probably could have handled better in terms of like the rest of the gaming community, but also whatever.
Kelly: It is what it is now.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So we've both played this.
Codey: Neither of us have beat it.
Codey: Um, but I guess like, Kelly, what were your 1st thoughts, um, for suppressions of the game and thoughts, and like how much gameplay time do you have in it?
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And then also like, what are you playing it on?
Kelly: Oh my god, uh, let me check SteamX.
Kelly: So I'm playing it on my computer.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Um, Which is, so I played Hollow Night entirely handheld on the Switch.
Kelly: Um, so I think like that alone is like a big change because now I have like, you know, a big computer monitor to play it on.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, which is nice.
Kelly: I have 80 hours in.
Kelly: Which is funny because I think I'm a maybe halfway.
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Also, I will note, like, I really love backtracking and like just exploring everything and like every time I get a new mechanic, I'm like, gotta go back and check out.
Kelly: You know, the places I marked off that I couldn't reach before or something.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: So like for me, I think like both Holiday and Silk Song are like about the exploration and like finding secrets and like kind of just like traversing around a lot.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, so like, immediately I was just like, I think like any minor worry was immediately swayed as soon as I started playing the game because it just, it just feels like an improvement upon holiday night.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like, it's the same vibe, like, it's so immersive, the the backgrounds and the music are so beautiful, like everything just...
Kelly: I think comes together so nicely in that same way.
Kelly: Um,
Kelly: And then I think they improved, you know, some of some of the mechanics, like, how long it is a very simple game.
Kelly: At base level.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like the mechanics are very simple.
Kelly: You have very little things that you can add onto your move set.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: And it's more about how you use those like simple mechanics.
Kelly: Um, and I think like, Silk Song still has that same concept, but there are areas that they expanded upon.
Kelly: Which I think is fun because I think it lets you as like the player kind of, it gives you more options on how you want to play the game.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: So I think that's very interesting, like very fun.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And it.
Codey: Yeah, it creates different like paths of playing the game and different because there's just different styles.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: It reminds me a lot.
Codey: I played World of Warcraft, and it reminds me of a lot of like, at 1st you were like, oh, I play a hunter, and so you know exactly what that means.
Codey: But then later there were specialisations that you could do.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And so then it was like, oh, I'm a marksmanship hunter.
Codey: And then it's like, okay, I know exactly, like that's different than if you were a survival hunter or whatever.
Codey: And so it's, you know, talking to some people and being like, oh, what, um, I can't even remember what they're called.
Kelly: I know, I know, I know.
Kelly: I'm like blanking on it.
Kelly: so hard right now.
Codey: But like, there's different.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Kelly: It's like the crests.
Codey: Yeah, there's a different different crusts that you can have and it's like, oh, what crust are you playing?
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: What, what, um, items are you using?
Kelly: Like what, what, um, tools do you have like equipped?
Codey: Yes, yeah.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Codey: Um, what tools do you have equipped and like what? I think the one thing, so one thing that was different that got me when I 1st started playing is Hornet.
Codey: So in Hollow Night, the Hollow Night, like it, when you go down, like you go straight down, like when you're jumping or whatever.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yes.
Codey: And Hornet goes kind of like at an angle to the side and that messed me up.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: But later there's a crest that basically lets you go back to the previous. And I'm like always doing that crunch.
Kelly: Yes.
Kelly: So it's so funny because I played this game at the same time as like another one of my friends and she was having a miserable time with the pogoing because of that.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: And honestly, I, I did not think that I could like pogoing more with a diagonal.
Kelly: I love it.
Kelly: I think it's, I don't know.
Kelly: I don't know why.
Kelly: I have not changed from.
Kelly: I have not changed to like the crust that makes you go down.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: I think I did try it once and I like died almost immediately and I was like, I'm not doing this.
Kelly: Like, I don't know, my brain, I did struggle with it at 1st in like that hunter, um, area.
Kelly: And then I think as soon as I figured it out, my brain was just like, yeah, you got it.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Go ahead.
Kelly: So, like, you're not the only person I've heard have issues with that.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: And obviously, like, they have a crest in the game to help you with it.
Kelly: So I think that is interesting, like, you know.
Kelly: But yeah, it did mess me up really bad like the 1st few times.
Kelly: Like, I just kept missing everything.
Codey: Well, and a lot of people, like it's, the game was a lot more fluid as well.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And so a lot of people like saw, like, you can adjust, once you, if you can adapt to it, like, you can fit, like, you can figure it out, but I just was so, you know, if I push down and I'm trying and I'm trying to pogo off of something, I'm expecting to go down.
Kelly: Yeah, which I think is like a natural expectation.
Kelly: Um, but I did want to go back to one thing you said, like, about how, um, all of these options give you different paths.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Which I do think is also really cool because I do think it, um,
Kelly: Expands on the freedom in general, like in Holland, you could kind of go anyway and still progress the story unless there was like a hard, Stop, and even then a lot of the time, you could find a way to fenagle around it.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: And so like you could do the story and basically any order you wanted as long as you hit like, like a few main markers, you know?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, And I think that kind of like having this option to like also do that with your character is like the next kind of step in that as well.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: So I think that just adds like more of this like, free movement idea, you know?
Codey: Um, and the, you don't start with all the crusts, like there's the start, you get the hunter crust at 1st and then you can go acquire the other crests.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So some folks, like, if you've played the game and you're trying to replay through again, you're like, okay, well, I know I need to go to Graymoor to get the Reaper Crust or wherever, like the in the chapel of the Reaper.
Codey: Like I have to go get this crust.
Codey: And so then you can kind of beeline right for that area because you know that that's what you want. Um, So yeah, I think that was like my initial thing was like, oh, I hate that.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: But, and then there's different like abilities with like the spears, um, or like silk abilities, like how you throw your silk, how you use your silk, because instead of just having like just your sword, um, or your needle, I guess.
Codey: Um, you also have these like silk abilities that you can do where you can like throw your silk or you can like heal yourself or whatever.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And that just adds another layer of complexity.
Codey: Like, I'm a big, like, heel person.
Codey: But some people just like run in full bore and they have like a silk ability that is offensive rather than defensive. And it's like, well, you know, uh, ain't no problem if I just don't get hit.
Kelly: Me too.
Codey: And I'm like, okay, but I get hit.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: But like, I think that also, like, it's that, like, goes back to obviously all the different play styles, but like, I think that's like what's so fun about the different crests and like the different, um, like the silk and everything, like, um, you can decide.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Oh, I know I'm not going to get hit.
Kelly: So I'm going to take something that gives me double damage, but lets me dole out double damage also. Like, that risk is so high, but also so rewarding if you know that you're like capable of it.
Codey: Hmm.
Kelly: Like I, I don't, I don't really do that one.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: No, I don't either.
Kelly: That one's not for me.
Kelly: Um, but yeah, like I think I think like the silk is like such an interesting extension on like the magic of Hollow Night, because like you had like force spells.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: And like, that's it.
Kelly: And you didn't have any real ability to change how they worked, like they were just the spells you got.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, so like, I mean, like there's so much more in terms of like mechanics going on like across the whole game.
Kelly: Like you have, like there, you have to think a lot.
Kelly: There's definitely a lot of thinking.
Codey: Yeah, and there's certain things that are definitely better for you in different areas.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Like one of the tools allows it so that like if you're on lava or something, like you're, you don't take as much damage or whatever and it's like, okay, well, you clearly need that to like get, get to a certain area.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: So it is kind of more like you're locked in, um, to a specific...
Kelly: Yeah, that one, that one's so good to like, um, switch on and off, but like definitely not like a permanent.
Codey: Yeah, that's...
Kelly: Which, again, like, is like kind of like similar to like the charm setup in Hollow Night, but like, I like the way they changed it in the game.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, because also with the crest, you have different slot amounts.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Per like your tools and your defensive items and everything.
Kelly: So you can really like customise how you want to, um, use them.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And then it's fun to, like, when you're in the game and you, you remember what all of these things mean and then you're like, and then you see like someone else's play and you're like, like set up and you're like, what is going on?
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah, like, what do you mean you're not throwing, uh, you're not throwing poison traps and poison arrows and everything?
Codey: I do the same thing.
Kelly: Like, what do you mean?
Kelly: I love a good trap.
Codey: The one, the one thing that sucks with that, though, is like if you get stuck in an area.
Kelly: I'm sorry.
Codey: So like the poison or like some of the things that you throw rely on you having like beetle shards, like shards that you get from like things that, and if you, there are some spots where like you get stuck to a point where you have to beat the next boss to like move forward.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yes.
Codey: And if you die like over and over and over again, eventually it's just like you don't have any anymore.
Codey: And it's like,
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: Yep, that's why I have hoarded a...
Kelly: I had a stockpile of like hoarded charts. To like crack open, which I do really like like that in the beads.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: That you can like, um, make them into a somewhat more permanent item that doesn't, uh, disintegrate if you die too many times.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, that, like, kind of evens out the rough edge of a rogue light or a rogue game.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: It, it's, it definitely gives you, it's, it gives you some sort of comfort.
Codey: Yeah, like, oh, I have all this money, but I'm actually just gonna string it together so that when I die, it doesn't go anywhere.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: Like, how smart, just put it on some rosaries.
Codey: Hell yeah.
Codey: Um, okay, so I kind of want I want to talk a little bit about the story.
Codey: So, Hornet herself is one of the bosses that you fight in the original Hollow Night game.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So you see her from the perspective of having to fight her and how and she's like formidable.
Codey: Um, and I don't think you kill her.
Kelly: Oh, yeah.
Codey: I think she's she just, you defeat her at different points in that game and it's, she like, she's like, 0 yes, you are a mighty warrior and then she like bails.
Kelly: No.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Yeah, yeah.
Kelly: She's like, oh, cool.
Kelly: I respect you a little bit more now each time we fight.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: She's like, oh, I won't stop you from going forward now.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Um, so this game, this is entirely like you are playing her.
Codey: So you're hornet.
Codey: And, um, I found this blurb of, uh, she finds herself in the depths of an unknown kingdom called Farloom, which seems to be haunted by silk and song.
Codey: It is up to Hornet to ascend to the citadel and uncover the truth and defeat an unknown entity in order to set the inhabitants of Farloom free from its control.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and I like this little blurb.
Codey: I don't remember, I'm bad.
Codey: I don't remember what website I found on this album.
Codey: Um, but it, like, kind of juxtaposes silk song with the original game, where, so silks, uh, the original game was in a place called Hollowness.
Codey: Uh, or Hollow Nest.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Codey: I don't know how you want to say it.
Codey: Um, so Farlum is, instead of descending into darkness, because that's what Hollow Nest is, like you go underground, and Farlum, you're ascending and on a pilgrimage towards the shiny, I mean, you're not doing a pilgrimage, but like there are a ton of other bugs that are doing the pilgrimage and they talk about how like they're, they go up to the citadel and, um, it's like a rite of passage almost.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and yeah.
Kelly: So can I actually, oh, sorry, go, go on, go on.
Kelly: I have a I have a point to add on to that after the end.
Codey: Please, no, actually, you say.
Kelly: Um, so I was going to say, I think it is very interesting because, so also, um, between the 2 games you have a lot of like religion.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And in in Hollow Night, um, there is a loss of your gods. So, like, the gods are all dead, basically, or like the one that has taken over is rotting everything to its core because the other gods died.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, and you're you're descending into the darkness, but in Farloom, you have all of these pilgrims.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: Heading towards the uh, the sacred land, essentially, to make their pilgrimage.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, and they get to ascend.
Kelly: Like, I think that's just like, it's very simple, but like also, I think, continues this like theme really well.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, and I think it's, like, interesting because when you when they do that.
Codey: Like, in Hollow Night, in Hollow Nest, it's like you are very aware that this land is unwell and like something is wrong and you are trying to make it right.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And in this game, you are ascending and it seems like everything's fine.
Codey: And the further up you go, the more you're like, uh, oh.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Oh.
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: It's like, and and the original game, like once you get to the end and you're, like, and you are defeating, quote unquote, the big bad.
Codey: Like, there's a part where you're like, oh, this is not a like this, this is like not a bad...
Kelly: Yeah, the, the, the, yes, like, uh, your definition of like good and evil and like, why this is happening and like all of that are kind of questioned. Heavily.
Codey: Oh, like it, that's the subversion of the expectation.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And this game does the same thing just kind of like in the other direction.
Kelly: So.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and so this blurb talked about silk as control.
Codey: So as you're going through this area, there's a lot of organ, a lot of bugs that are alive and they're up and about.
Codey: There's this one, um, gosh, what is her name?
Codey: She is so sweet.
Kelly: Oh, uh, chakra?
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Uh, Oh.
Codey: Well, no, I love chakra too.
Codey: Uh, the, the one that's singing.
Kelly: Oh, Sherma, Sherma's my favourite.
Codey: Germa.
Kelly: I've been, so I was waiting for Sherma since the game that announced basically.
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Kelly: I have a little Sherma Plushie, and I dressed up as Sherma for Halloween.
Codey: Oh, that's so great.
Codey: She's so sweet.
Codey: She's just like,
Kelly: I love her so much.
Codey: She's just like the, I'm gonna go up there and everything's fine and everything's good and she's just singing her song like.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: She's like, I'm gonna heal the world with song.
Kelly: It's fine.
Codey: Yeah, and she, like, throughout all of it, like, I feel like, at least to the point where I've got, like, she's, there's parts where it's very clearly dangerous, and then, and like, you've just, like, crawled through a battle, and, like, you've barely made it out alive, and Sherma's just, like, there, like, hi, you made it.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Let me sing you a song to fix you.
Codey: It's just like, how did you get here and why are you not?
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: Um, so there's, there's, uh, that.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: There's like the bugs that are sentient, I guess, and like where and able to control themselves with and there are others that you'll be walking by and there's like dead bodies, places or whatever.
Codey: And then suddenly like a, like silk kind of comes down to this animation, um, of something striking the body and it's silk.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: It's like a silk spear style thing.
Codey: Like, it's like, and suddenly that body is up and moving.
Codey: Um, and so it's like silk is control because the, there's like a puppet master at the top that can like kind of control all of these different things down below.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Which I think is also pretty, um, similar to the, uh, the radiant taking over, you know, ratings taking over with, with all of that, but also very different, like, because one is a hive mind and one is more of a puppeteering.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: Hmm.
Kelly: So like I think like the similarities are very, like, interesting, but also clearly not exactly the same.
Codey: Yes.
Codey: And the closer you get to the citadel, uh, the stronger these are.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So like the more of the more that you're going to find, but also the stronger the enemies that are, um, controlled with silk are, um, yeah, it's it's very interesting.
Codey: And you're always like, hmm, who is the puppet domaster?
Codey: Um, and then song, this song is hypnosis.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And the bells and music flow through the architecture, the weapons and the enemies, and this constant song guides and ensnares the kingdom's people.
Codey: Um, there's definitely the part of like the songs that are holy, that are like like Sherma, like trying, like saying she's going to heal the world, but there are some songs.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And there's once you're in the citadel, there's like a part of it where you have to uncover some harmonies and there's these, I want to say 3 different harmonies of like the different, some different, um, factions within the citadel that you can acquire their harmony and then you play it all together.
Codey: And like the part when you, I don't know if you, I didn't, I, so I didn't, I don't think I got to this part, but I watched my husband play it and there's a part where like you unlock all 3 of them together and there's a cut scene and then,
Kelly: I don't think I got to that either, but I know the area that you're talking about with like the coral chamber area, right?
Codey: The.
Codey: Yes, the coral chamber, yeah.
Kelly: Like, yeah, okay.
Codey: And the music is like, I have goosebumps right now.
Codey: Like this.
Codey: Christopher Larkin, man.
Codey: Like...
Kelly: Oh my god, I have, I have the 1st vinyl set.
Codey: Oh.
Kelly: Like extended from that and I still get goosebumps from like, I think the Sisters of Battle still gets me every time, like it is just like such insane boss music.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah. Oh, there's another, what's the other one that's, um,
Codey: Uh, in in the original game.
Codey: There's the one that's like an area.
Codey: It's like a, not a chapel.
Codey: It's like a morgue area, cathedral.
Kelly: Oh, the resting grounds or...
Codey: It's a cathedral, a spire.
Codey: I'm going to look it up, but, um,
Kelly: Oh, not not un.
Kelly: Um, because there are a few like cathedrally looking places.
Codey: Oh my gosh, I just looked up Hollow Nightmap and these maps are huge, y'all.
Kelly: They are so big.
Codey: My goodness.
Kelly: Well, that's so just to go back, that is what delayed the game because they just cannot help themselves from discontinuing to add more and more in.
Codey: They just kept going.
Kelly: Which is so funny, like, which I love.
Kelly: Like, again, my whole, my favourite, I like, I like, I like the bosses.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: But my favourite part of the game is exploring, and like, I just think they make such a good map.
Codey: It's in, I think it's in the City of Tears.
Kelly: Oh, the sole symptom.
Codey: The soul sanctum.
Codey: The music and the soul sanctum.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Codey: Ah, it's so...
Kelly: Oh god, yeah, that is, that is some good, that, the whole soul sanctum area is like, ooh.
Codey: Well, not boss sucks.
Kelly: Yeah, I hate that boss.
Codey: Like, it's a great box.
Kelly: It is.
Codey: He just sucks so bad.
Codey: And so like whenever I hear that music, my heart rate is just like, ugh.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Oh, and then like Dung Defender.
Kelly: I think that's um, that's when my controller started dying.
Codey: Oh no.
Kelly: Or I was getting like, um, you know, like uh, stick drift.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Which was not helping with that boss.
Codey: Oh.
Codey: Not something you want.
Kelly: No.
Codey: Um.
Kelly: Like that whole, that whole game has such good music, honestly.
Codey: Yeah, and and this one as well, like, there's a whole part where you are getting, you're trying to get those 3 harmonies so that you can, um, like have them sing it. And then basically like all together, it will unlock like another stage.
Kelly: like so does this one.
Codey: Like you'll be able to ascend a little bit further.
Codey: Um, And it is just so good.
Codey: I don't know, I guess I don't know where I was going to go with that.
Codey: And then like.
Codey: The last part that says is faith and pilgrimage.
Codey: So Farlum's faithful don't descend, they ascend.
Codey: Um, and the silk spool symbolises this journey.
Codey: So your almost health bar, basically.
Codey: No, no, it's not your health bar.
Codey: It's like your magic, like,
Kelly: Um, yeah, I was gonna say like magic or like, um, not energy, but like, I guess like mana.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Yeah, so like magic, yeah, it all.
Codey: Yeah, and as you go through the game, like it gets longer and and you have more health and and it's just a little bit bigger and you're sturdier and stuff. And I think like the more silk you have, the, I think, I guess I don't really know what it's trying to say.
Codey: trying to see if I can spin a tale of like, you're more connected with the faith when you have more silk, but I don't know if that's necessarily true.
Codey: But.
Kelly: It could be.
Kelly: I mean, there's also, um, so to dive into a little hollow night and silk song, lore, um, hornet is half weaver, which is like spidery.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, and then half worm.
Kelly: So, like, naturally, she does have a connection to the silk, but, like, also, it's very interesting to see the silk within Farloom itself.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like, because it's like, like, I expected it to just be more so of just hornets skill.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: At 1st like before the game came out.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Um, but there's clearly so much tied into it, even though, Um, I think Hornet is the last lever.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, I think that's also like something that's so in the original game, like Hornet is such an anomaly.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: It's like all of these other bugs, like have certain mechanics, have certain whatever, like you know, you understand how they're fighting.
Kelly: Yes.
Codey: And then she comes in and she has like this silk and this threat and this needle and like, it's like, who are you?
Kelly: Throwing spikes and she moves so fast and.
Codey: And she's clearly like different.
Codey: And then, and this game starts off with, she's in Hollow Nest, but then she gets abducted and brought to Farloom.
Codey: And she starts realising, like she, as you're ascending, she's also kind of uncovering a little bit about, I think, her past as well, because she thought that all of the weavers are dead.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And I think they all are, but like the entity at the top of the citadel, like, has a connection to the weavers.
Kelly: Yeah, and you see other.
Codey: And so it's like also her, yeah.
Kelly: You see other characters along the way too that clearly have like connections to the weavers, even if they're not weavers themselves, like, um, Oh, what's that one in Sinners Road?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Stick.
Codey: I hate sinners.
Kelly: Oh, God.
Kelly: Centres Road is like actually like disgusting.
Kelly: Like, I don't know how they did such a good job of making such a vile, like I feel dirty.
Codey: Yes, 100%.
Kelly: It's, it's, it's crazy.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Codey: I think also like all of the, I think part of it is in that area, like things stick to you and things, like, if you...
Kelly: Yes.
Kelly: Um, if you go in the water.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: There's like things that will eat you and then will start eating your silk.
Codey: Um, and it's just, you feel dirty and you feel like infected and lit.
Kelly: It, it's, yep.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: And it's like, it's like you can't get.
Codey: Mm-hmm, Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And like, I think that's like, okay, to go to the water, though, like, 0 my god, the 1st time I fell in the water, ugh.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: Because also, like, Sinners Road is hard and like, you're already struggling enough as it is and it's like, just kick me when I'm down.
Kelly: Like, thank you.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: But I think I had like, um, I had it, I didn't have enough stored, um, Did you have yourself, but you also have, um,
Kelly: On the side, like, you're useable.
Codey: Mhm.
Kelly: However, yeah, yeah, like, um, It's like you have, you have your health.
Codey: The shards.
Kelly: Oh yeah, you have that health and then you have your your silk and like, if you don't cure yourself fast enough of the water, like it just eats everything and then you're stuck.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: You're screwed.
Codey: Yep Yep.
Codey: And then like, and they're still there.
Codey: And if you start gaining more silk, the like silk eater things that are infected with you are like, oh, cool, more silk. And you're like, ow, and you have to like get enough to be able to like heal yourself and like get rid of all of them.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: And then you're stuck in Sarah's Road with like nothing.
Codey: But...
Codey: Yeah, because they just consume all of your resources.
Kelly: Talk about parasitic bugs.
Codey: Parasitic box for sure.
Codey: Um, yeah, it's just, it's, I guess that's like the gist of it without like fully going into spoiler mode or anything and I don't, neither of us have finished it.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So like, I don't, it's, we don't have to talk, talk about it anymore than that.
Kelly: Yeah, it's like, I didn't want to talk about like what Styx does.
Codey: I, like,
Codey: Right.
Codey: Um, but I guess like, the final, like, final thoughts about this game or, like, did you have any specific questions?
Codey: What, like, what are your favourite parts of it?
Codey: Um...
Kelly: Um, I know I'm like kind of a sicko, but I do love, uh, the hunter's marsh.
Codey: Oh my gosh, why do you?
Kelly: I also I love pogoing.
Codey: Why do you hate yourself?
Kelly: Like I.
Kelly: I think it's so fun.
Kelly: I think pogoing is like the greatest thing you could ever.
Codey: That's.
Kelly: I think, but I think that's engrained in me from Hollow Night, because like, like you had to do like some crazy pog going in there without the bell.
Kelly: I think the bell changes everything for me, like, I think that gives me, So much more freedom to, like, make mistakes while I'm pogoing, I guess.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: So I think it like takes some of the pressure off.
Codey: Yep.
Kelly: But also, I don't know.
Kelly: I love platforming.
Kelly: So, like, I just think it's it's like fun in a really sick way.
Codey: Yeah, there's there's just some times in platforming where you need to just like step away because like your brain is not like doing the thing. Um...
Kelly: Yeah, oh absolutely.
Kelly: Like, I will throw myself at a, um, area over and over again, but also at a certain point, I'm just like, I'm going to go check out something else because clearly this isn't working out for me right now.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And then like the next time you go to that area, you just like one shot it.
Kelly: Yeah, it's it's so easy.
Codey: You're like, what the heck?
Kelly: It's so easy.
Kelly: Um, I'm trying to think, there was like a fair amount of bosses I liked.
Kelly: I think some of them, I mean, they're they're hard.
Kelly: They're all hard.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: You know?
Codey: There's not, this game does not pull punches.
Kelly: Who is who is the one in The Fairfields, the giant mecca.
Kelly: I loved that one.
Kelly: That was the one in the hot lava area.
Codey: Oh, and you like walk by him the 1st time?
Kelly: Yes, and I nearly hit my pants the 1st time I walked by him because I was like, I have to run, like we're running.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: It's so, I mean, it's, it's so fun that the, that they do this because like the 1st time you go through this area, like there's this, there's this thing in the background and you're like, okay, clearly this is something that's going to get me.
Kelly: This is gonna set off something right now.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And like, I remember like 1st coming up and seeing it like peripherally and then being like, I'm going to go stock up on some stuff.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: Yep, I was like, I'm gonna go save my game.
Codey: Yeah, and then and then you go.
Kelly: And make sure I hit a bench.
Codey: And then you go through it and nothing happens and you're like, oh, okay, but then when you try and leave.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: Okay.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: Oh, that was great.
Kelly: Then it gets you.
Kelly: Um, I I can't remember.
Kelly: I got killed somewhere and then I got thrown into the prison, which was, I thought, really fun.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: Yep Yep.
Kelly: And also terrifying because it's like you have this combination of like, 0 my god, where am I?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: This is a rogue light, so if I die, I'm going to lose a ton of stuff.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Please show me a bench.
Kelly: You know what I mean?
Kelly: Like, I think that that pressure.
Kelly: It makes like something like getting work to a new place where you have no idea where you are, very scary, like much more scary.
Codey: They, they also have benches. That are traps.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: Uh, the mimics, like not mimics, but yeah, like the trap benches, like, okay.
Kelly: Okay, like trust nothing.
Codey: Like you get to a spot and you're like, oh, thank goodness, there's a bench and you sit and then it just like kills you.
Kelly: I can't even remember where that one was, but there is at least two, I think, and I remember the 1st one got me so good after that I was so cautious.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, like, they just, it really just makes you, you, it makes you check everywhere, everywhere, like, because there's so many secret rooms and secret passages and stuff, so you're always checking everything, but also then, like, you come upon something and you're like, I don't think, like, you go and you see this giant thing in the background, and you're like, I don't know if I can trust this.
Kelly: Um.
Kelly: Mm.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: There's been so many times where I found like with clearly a passage to a new area and I'm like, I don't know if I want.
Kelly: I think like the 1st time I got it to Sinners Road.
Kelly: Like I was like, hmm, I don't want to be here right now.
Codey: Okay, yeah.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, especially because when you 1st get there, you, the 1st things you see are those, um, like possum thingies that like jump on you.
Kelly: Oh, the the muckroaches?
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Yeah, those are horrendous.
Codey: Um, they like jump on you and they can kind of like grab you and they do a ton of dance.
Codey: Like, I think that was, that was an area where the previous area you were getting like one tick damage or something and then you get there and you're suddenly getting 2 tick damage, like double damage and you're like, what the heck?
Kelly: Oh my god.
Kelly: Yep.
Kelly: And these things like chase you down like they're hound dogs, like they get you.
Codey: Yeah, yeah.
Codey: And they're not, like, you can't really cheese them that much, like they're...
Kelly: No, you just kind of have to like, uh, like have a shred.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Um.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: I think Hunter's March is also a really hard area.
Codey: Like it's a bunch of ant people.
Codey: Um, like ant bosses and they were also really brutal.
Kelly: Yes.
Kelly: They're tough, yeah.
Codey: Um...
Kelly: Which I think like that area, though, is good for like, I think like they do a good job of like setting the areas up at the start, especially to help you.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Gain confidence.
Codey: Yes.
Kelly: In like the skills you'll need going forward.
Kelly: Unfortunately, like as hard as some of those areas are, because like, some of those ants, I was like, get away from it.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: I was like, I am jumping.
Kelly: I pokoed over so many of them.
Codey: Yeah, there's like some that you're like, okay, I'll take the time to like sit here and like fight you.
Codey: And then there's other ones where I'm like, goodbye.
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, but yeah, I mean, I love the whole game.
Kelly: I love all the characters in it.
Kelly: Like, I think it's,
Kelly: So fun.
Kelly: I want to play it forever, even though I stopped playing it because it takes a lot of energy.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: That's the only reason I stopped playing.
Codey: Um.
Kelly: Um, but so what were your favourite parts so far?
Codey: So I really love chakra.
Codey: Um, I think she, so she is the equivalent of like the map guy.
Kelly: I love her.
Codey: So there's a map bug in the 1st game.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and in this game, that's what she is.
Codey: She's trying to find her, I can't remember the word that she uses, but like basically like her trainer or like her boss and her mentor and her people are like a warrior people.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Like, yeah.
Codey: And, like, she is just a badass.
Codey: Like she's just really cool.
Kelly: She's so cool.
Kelly: Like corner first, so corner 1st the Mac guy in the 1st one.
Kelly: He's such a nerd.
Codey: Yeah, he's a nerd.
Kelly: Like, he is so clearly a nerd, but she's like such a badass, like, adventuring fighting.
Codey: Yeah, she's like a warrior that is happens to be mapping it as she goes and she'll share it with you because she, um, respects you.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: game recognises game, basically.
Kelly: Yeah, yeah.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: I think she's supposed to be like a paper.
Codey: That would make sense.
Kelly: like the way her shape is also and like the colours, yeah.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: That would make sense.
Codey: So that's she's a character.
Codey: I was, I spoke with one entomologist once that wanted to do a panel in New York City Comic-Con about the the bugs of silk song.
Codey: Um, and he, we ended up not doing it, but like I was going to be on the panel as well. And we were talking about, we were talking about being, um, like dressing up as characters and I wanted to dress up as chakra.
Kelly: Oh, that would have been.
Codey: Like I had looked up some cosplays that people have.
Kelly: Oh, that would have been sick.
Codey: I might still do it eventually, but because it was really cool, but, um,
Kelly: It's like stuff like that has to be hard though, because it's like, there's clearly some bugs in this game that are based on real bugs and then there's clearly, um, like I think most of the pilgrims are just...
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: They're just, they're just bugs.
Codey: They're just, yeah, the amorphous word bug.
Codey: Um, for sure.
Codey: Uh, and then the, my other favourite is the Bell Beast.
Codey: So.
Kelly: Uh that's my favourite also.
Codey: Yeah, so she...
Kelly: I think the 2 of them were so good.
Codey: In the original game, there's the, his name is the last stag, and he's a stag beetle, and there's these like kind of subway systems, basically, to get from point A to point B, and you can call him and he'll he'll take you there.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and I always get a little emotional with his storyline because he's, it's, he's like the last stag.
Codey: But then at one point in the game, I think near the end, you come upon an area and there's just like a bunch of dead stag beetles, but then there's like an egg.
Codey: And then the next time you, and the eggs been hatch, and the next time you see him, his name is the old stag, and it's just like, screaming.
Kelly: Yes, and the egg's been hatched.
Kelly: Yes.
Kelly: Yeah.
Kelly: Oh my god.
Kelly: I think I cried when that happened.
Kelly: Like I, I love that.
Kelly: I love the old stag.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Uh, and so this, uh, the Bell Beast is this, this game's, uh, last stag, where when you 1st encounter her, she, actually, she's a boss, actually, like, she comes out and she's, like, grumpy and she's, you have to fight her and you basically fight her into not, not necessarily submission, but I think she, like, just realises that you don't want to hurt.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: Your friend?
Codey: Yeah, that you don't want to hurt her and like you're just defending yourself.
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And then she becomes she becomes like your, your way to get through things, but like, you can interact with her.
Codey: I think they've, the developers have said that like hitting her with your sword is like petting her.
Codey: Um,
Kelly: Yeah.
Codey: And then at one point in the game, you get your, you make your needle into, um, an instrument called the needle in.
Codey: And if you play that around her, she starts like purring at you.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: And it's, she's just so sweet.
Codey: And then there is like a late game, really cute thing that happens, but I don't want to spoil it.
Kelly: He's so cute.
Kelly: I don't know if I reached that part yet, so.
Codey: Um, But she is just so great.
Codey: I have a tattoo of her like.
Kelly: What do you, what bug do you...
Codey: I mean, she's like an isopod.
Kelly: That's okay, that's what I also assumed.
Kelly: Like she clearly has like that isopod look.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Going on.
Codey: Um, I guess I have.
Kelly: Um, every time I every time I see her, I have to jump across the bells on top.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like better.
Kelly: I can't, like, I can't not.
Codey: just so good.
Codey: Yeah, so she has too many legs to be an insect.
Codey: So isopod is fine.
Codey: Um, I wonder what, let me see if the trivia, there's like trivia.
Codey: Hitting the Bellevue is considered to be petting her.
Codey: This also occasionally causes her to purr in response.
Codey: Yeah, I don't really see anything that's like, here's how, here's what she's supposed to be.
Codey: Um, but I would probably just say ice pod.
Codey: cutey patootie.
Kelly: The...
Codey: Oh, and she's trapped in silk too, but she's still, like, I think when you 1st find her, she's trapped in silk and you like let her out and she's and you're like, I'm going to help you and you let her out and then she just starts attacking you.
Kelly: Oh, okay.
Codey: You're like, what the?
Codey: I just released you from a bunch of silk.
Codey: But she was just scared.
Codey: But.
Codey: Yeah, I mean, I think that that's the, that's the, my overarching opinions of Sulk Song and without getting into like spoilers and stuff. And, um, I, I mean, I want to just, I kind of want to just start up a new game now that we're done talking about this.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: And literally, when you reached out to me, I was like, do I just start playing one?
Kelly: But I was, I was playing that other game and like I, I knew I couldn't.
Kelly: I can't play multiple games.
Kelly: I'm not capable of like that kind of commitment.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Um, but yes, I think you've, you've reinfected.
Codey: I think I think we've done it to each other because this is this is like the bug is in me now.
Codey: I want to play it again.
Codey: And it's like visiting old friends too.
Codey: It's like, I want to go back and interact with these characters and like see them again and maybe finish their stories this time.
Kelly: Yep.
Codey: Um, so we'll definitely do that.
Codey: Um, well, do you have anything that you would like to share with the audience, Kelly?
Kelly: Um, no, I don't really do anything online.
Codey: Cool.
Codey: Um, I mean, I'll share that we're about to live pretty close, so we cannot hang out.
Kelly: Oh, yeah.
Kelly: Yeah, we gotta meet up in the...
Codey: Pretty stoked about that.
Codey: Um, pretty stoked about that.
Codey: Um, I don't really have anything to share either.
Codey: You guys have heard us yap for a long time now, so I'll stop.
Codey: You can find the podcast on Tumblr and Blue Sky at THS Pod.
Codey: You can go to our website, harvestseason.club, to access feedback and links and transcripts and the show notes so you can see some pictures of what a lace bug looks like.
Codey: Um, and then, uh, you can access our Patreon at patreon.com slash GHS pod.
Codey: And if you do so, you can get access to our Slack community, which I will post a photo of the Beatles stuck in the caddisfly.
Codey: Um, thing into that and so maybe some other fun, fun pictures uh, from my personal collection.
Codey: You also get access to the greenhouse episodes.
Codey: We haven't had greenhouses in a while, but Kev is rare and to record some.
Codey: So I'm sure we will probably get some soon.
Codey: Um, But yeah, thank you, Kelly, for joining me.
Kelly: Oh, no, thank you.
Codey: Thank you, Al, for.
Kelly: Always loved her.
Codey: Yeah, thank you, Alpha, editing this very long episode.
Codey: And thank you, listeners, for listening, and until next time.
Codey: Have a good harvest.
Codey: Goodbye.
Theme Tune: The harvest season is created by Al McKinley, with support from our patrons, including our pro farmers, Kevin, Stewart, and Elisa.
Theme Tune: Our art is done by Mike the Brave, and our music is done by Nick Burgess.
Theme Tune: Feel free to visit our website, harvestseason.club for show notes and links to things we discussed in this episode.
Codey: And then we go to time dot is, and let me know.
Kelly: Oh, this is new.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So we're gonna clap on 30?
Codey: Is that okay?
Codey: Okay.
Kelly: Yep, okay.
Codey: And we never hear each other clap.
Codey: It's very interesting.
Kelly: You know, I was literally, I was like, uh, was that just me clapping?
Codey: Nope.
Kelly: That's so funny.
Codey: I don't think I've ever heard unless we clap like out of sync.
Codey: I have never heard the other person clap, and, but out...
Kelly: Okay, well, I think that's like a good thing, right?
Codey: Yeah.
Kelly: Like...
Codey: Well, and I'll try to explain it to me once and I just was, I, I, my brain went somewhere else.
Codey: I don't know.
Kelly: Yeah, apparently my computer clock is 12nd ahead, so.
Codey: Ooh, mine says I was perfectly on time, so.
Kelly: Interesting too.
Kelly: Nice.
Kelly: How do you even fix that?
Kelly: Like, what do you, I thought my computer was synced.
Kelly: Like, what do you mean?
Codey: I don't know
Kelly: Like, you know, like, I saw somebody on Discord who had like a mod that, like, let you see other people's time.
Kelly: And it said their time was off by like 2 seconds and she was on her phone.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Kelly: What do you mean your phone is off by 2 seconds?
Kelly: How do you even fix that?
Codey: Yeah, I, I mean, we used, you used to be able to like reset that on old dumb phones.
Kelly: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, but I have no idea how to do it now.
Kelly: Yeah, exactly.
Kelly: Like, like, that's not even something I consider being able to do or like having an issue with because I thought that was all handled for us.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: I don't know.